<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Commons assembled in Parliament concerning the rise and progresse of the grand rebellion in Ireland. Together vvith a multitude of examinations of persons of quality, whereby it may easily appear to all the world, who were, and still are the promoters of that cruell and unheard of rebellion. With some letters and papers of great consequence of the Earl of Antrims, which were intercepted. Also some letters of Mart, which were granted by the Lord Mohun, Sir Ralph Hopton, &amp;c. And likewise another from the rebells in Ireland, who term themselves, the supreme councel for the Catholique-cause. Ordered by the Commons in Parl. that this declaration, examinations, and letters, be forthwith printed and published: H. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <title>Proceedings. 1643-07</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83674</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2557A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204348</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897354</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897354</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132705</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83674)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132705)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2498:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Commons assembled in Parliament concerning the rise and progresse of the grand rebellion in Ireland. Together vvith a multitude of examinations of persons of quality, whereby it may easily appear to all the world, who were, and still are the promoters of that cruell and unheard of rebellion. With some letters and papers of great consequence of the Earl of Antrims, which were intercepted. Also some letters of Mart, which were granted by the Lord Mohun, Sir Ralph Hopton, &amp;c. And likewise another from the rebells in Ireland, who term themselves, the supreme councel for the Catholique-cause. Ordered by the Commons in Parl. that this declaration, examinations, and letters, be forthwith printed and published: H. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <title>Proceedings. 1643-07</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
                  <author>Antrim, Randal MacDonnell, Earl of, 1609-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Edw. Husbands, and are to be sold in the Middle-Temple,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Iuly 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another impression (Wing E2557) has "July 25, 1643" in imprint, and lacks the order to print on title page verso.</note>
                  <note>With no ornaments on A2v. Variant: outer forme of quire A partly reset. Imprint has "Iuly 25. 1642."; A2v has row of ornaments between text and catchword.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132705:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION Of the Commons aſſembled in PARLIAMENT; Concerning the Riſe and Progreſſe of <hi>The Grand Rebellion</hi> IN IRELAND TOGETHER VVith a multitude of <hi>Examinations</hi> of Perſons of quality, whereby it may eaſily appear to all the World, who were, and ſtill are the Promoters of that cruell and unheard of <hi>REBELLION.</hi> With ſome Letters and Papers of great conſequence of the Earl of <hi>Antrims,</hi> which were intercepted. Alſo ſome <hi>Letters of</hi> MART, which were granted by the Lord <hi>Mohun,</hi> Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> &amp;c. And likewiſe another from the Rebells in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who term themſelves, <hi>The</hi> SUPREME COUNCEL <hi>for the Catholique-Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ORdered by the Commons in Parl. That this Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Examinations, and Letters, be forthwith printed and publiſhed:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>H. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edw. Husbands,</hi> and are to be ſold in the Middle-Temple. Iuly 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:132705:2"/>
            <opener>
               <date>Die Martis, 25 Julii, 1643.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> That the Miniſters of every Pariſh within the Kingdom, ſhall read this Declaration in their ſeverall <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Chappels,</hi> on the next Faſt day the ſame ſhall come to their hands, after the ending of the firſt Sermon, and before the beginning of the next.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:132705:2"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He COMMONS in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament do obſerve, that the grand Deſigne of altering Religion throughout His Majeſties Dominions, had a more ſpeciall influence in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as being more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from view, and more propence to receive ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and therefore they think fit to call to minde (as introductive to that which follows) ſome particular footſteps, by which Popery hath been advanced, and true Religion diſcountenanced in that Kingdom, ſince the acceſſe of His Majeſtie to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond yeer of His Majeſties Raign, certain Propoſitions were ſet on foot in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the ſcope whereof was to fautour and indulge Popery in that Kingdom, as namely, to ſuſpend all proceedings againſt the Papiſts, for being marryed, or for procuring their children to be chriſtned by popiſh Prieſts, to allow the ſuing out of Liveries &amp; <hi>Outre Leſ-mains</hi> by the Papiſts, without taking the Oath of Supremacie; with many like Priviledges to the Papiſts. The Deſigne being to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:132705:3"/> bring in a more publique Tolleration of the popiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in that Kingdom, for a ſum of Money to be paid to His Majeſtie for the ſame. Theſe Propoſitions and Deſigne were ſo groſſe and ſcandalous, that even the then Biſhops of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by a writing under their hands bearing date the 26 of November, 1626. did make a Proteſtation, ſetting forth how grievous a ſin it was to conſent to ſuch Tolleration of Popery, and that to grant it in reſpect of any Money to be given, were to ſet Religion to ſale, and withall, the ſouls of the people whom Chriſt hath redeemed with his precious blood. And that, as it was a great ſin, ſo they did conceive it of moſt dangerous conſequence, as by the ſaid Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion herewith printed may appear: And although the Houſe of Commons in their Remonſtrance made in the third Yeer of His Majeſties Raigne, did truely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Folio 24.</note> that even then the Popiſh Religion was openly profeſt in every part of that Kingdome, that Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Nunneries were then newly erected and reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, with men and women of ſeverall Orders, that this might prove of evill conſequence, if not ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly repreſſed, therefore moſt humbly beſought His Majeſty, to lay the ſerious conſideration thereof to His Royall and pious heart, and that ſome ſpeedy courſe might be taken for redreſſe therein; Yet how this faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and timely advice of the Biſhops of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Commons of <hi>England</hi> was followed, and what ſpeedy courſe was taken for redreſſe therein, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by this which inſues. For,</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:132705:3"/>
            <p>IN the beginning of the Fourth yeer of His Majeſties Raigne, upon the agreement of certain Agents ſent from <hi>Ireland</hi> to His Majeſtie (all or moſt part of them being profeſſed Papiſts) theſe Propoſitions and Graces, with many like Additions, were granted and confirmed by His Majeſtie, in conſideration of One hundred and twenty thouſand pounds, to be levyed in three yeers upon the Kingdom in generall, as well upon the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants as upon the Papiſts: How great an encouragement to the Papiſts this was, and what an inſufferable preſſure to the Proteſtants, that beſides the illegall impoſing it upon them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their conſent in Parliament, they muſt be compelled to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe with their money, Tollerations and Immunities for the Papiſts, let even thoſe men judge who will be ſtiled the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and honeſt Proteſtants, whiles with all their faculties of body and minde, they ſtrive to advance Popery, and to root up the Proteſtant Religion, and the Liberty of the Subject.</p>
            <p>Many potent and notorious Papiſts have been created Peers by His Majeſtie, whereby the Votes of the Popiſh party in the Lords Houſe (too many before) are much encreaſed, and thoſe Papiſts become more powerfull and more exemplary in their reſpective countries, to the great encouragement and growth of Popery, and diſcouragement to the good people of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>That when by direction of the Lord Chancellor <hi>Loftus,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Cork,</hi> then Lords Juſtices, proceedings were begun againſt the Papiſts, upon the Statute of 2 <hi>Eliz.</hi> for not coming to Church, and the Iudges in their circuits gave that Statute in charge, and Indictments were framed thereupon; directions were ſent from <hi>England,</hi> to ſuſpend and ſtay all proceedings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Statute, when by taking the penalty impoſed by that Statute being Nine pence, for abſenting from Church Sundayes and Holy-dayes, the poor Proteſtants there might have been ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of many heavie payments and Taxes which were after im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon them, and the Papiſts either brought to conformity, or elſe kept ſo under, that this Rebellion; if not wholly preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet could not have proved ſo Univerſall, and ſo bloody as now it is.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:132705:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>That the late Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> being the Kings Lieutenant there, did by his great Favorite Sir <hi>George Ratcliff,</hi> one of His Majeſties Privie-Couneell of that Kingdom, hold correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie with the Popiſh Clergie, and particularly with <hi>Paul Harris</hi> a known Prieſt, who had both publique and private acceſſe to Sir <hi>George Ratcliff</hi> at all times, as well by night as by day.</p>
            <p>That in <hi>March,</hi> 1639. the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> carryed with him into <hi>Ireland,</hi> Sir <hi>Toby Matthews,</hi> a notorious, pernicious Engliſh Ieſuited Prieſt, (baniſhed at the beginning of this Parliament upon the importunity of both Houſes) lodged this Prieſt over againſt the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> the houſe where the Earl did him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf reſide, and from whence this Prieſt daily rode to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Maſſe-houſes in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and negotiated the engaging of the Papiſts of <hi>Ireland</hi> in the war againſt <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the late Lo: Chanc: <hi>Loftus</hi> and the E. of <hi>Cork</hi> were Lords Iuſtices, they endeavoured to ſuppreſſe the Maſſe-houſes in <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> and to convert them to pious uſes; one which was in the ſtreet called the <hi>Back-lane,</hi> they diſpoſed of to the Univerſity of <hi>Dublin,</hi> who placed a Rector, and Schollars in it, and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a weekly Lecture there; to which Lecture the Lords Iuſtices and State of <hi>Ireland</hi> did uſually reſort, to the great countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the Proteſtant Religion there; But after the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> came to the Government, the Lecture was put down, the Schollars diſplaced, and the houſe became a Maſſe-houſe, as formerly it had been.</p>
            <p>That divers Monaſteries and Nunneries were newly erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed immediately before the Rebellion brake forth in divers parts of that Kingdom: That at the <hi>Naas</hi> where the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> had his chief ſeat and reſort, Convents of Friars, namely, <hi>Auguſtines, Franciſcans, Dominicans,</hi> were not onely permitted, but alſo an houſe built there by the ſaid Earl, for an other purpoſe (as he pretended) ſoon after the building was converted to a Friery, by the connivence of the ſaid Earl.</p>
            <p>That the Popiſh Iriſh Army was kept on foot there for a long time after the beginning of this Parliament, contrary to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and frequent deſires of both Houſes of Parliament, and to the great furtherance of this Rebellion, by teaching thoſe bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous villains the knowledge of Arms under the notion of fighting againſt <hi>Scotland,</hi> but now made uſe of to extirpate both Engliſh and Scots from the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:132705:4"/>
            <p>And that Lead might not be wanting to the compleating of this intended Rebellion (as it had bin in the laſt great Rebellion there, to the great diſadvantage of the then Rebells) the Silver Mines of that Kingdom (which do afford great ſtore of Lead, and therefore fit onely to be in the hands of Proteſtants of known integrity) were farmed out by His Majeſtie to moſt pernicious Papiſts, namely, Sir <hi>George Hamilton,</hi> Sir <hi>Baſil Brook,</hi> &amp; the like; and upon the diſcovery of the Plot for the ſurpriſing of the City and Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> divers barrels of Muſquet-bullet were found (upon ſearch) in the houſe of the ſaid Sir <hi>George Hamilton</hi> in <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before this Rebellion brake forth, the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> (well knowing the ready way to endear his Prince, was to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his profit) had by a violent endeavour entitled His Majeſtie by Office to the whole counties of <hi>Roſcommon, Mayo, Slego, Galloway</hi> and <hi>Clare,</hi> and to a great part of the counties of <hi>Limerick</hi> and <hi>Tipperary;</hi> by which means a door was opened, not onely to increaſe His Majeſties revenue in a very great proportion, but therewith to ſettle a Plantation of Engliſh Proteſtants, to the advancement of Religion, and ſafety of that Kingdom; And however the proceedings of the Earl herein were not to be juſtified in all points, yet when the Committee was ſent from <hi>Ireland,</hi> at the beginning of this Parliament, to complain of divers grievances, they had no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular directions to mention this for one; neither did that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee ever attend His Majeſtie to complain thereof, or deſire a red reſſe therein, (conceiving the mentioning thereof wouldex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly diſtaſte His Majeſtie) untill His Majeſtie freely offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to depart with His Title to the former proprietors; But on the contrary, the Lords Iuſtices, and Councell of <hi>Ireland</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the great advantage of this ſervice, did by their Letters exceedingly importune His Majeſtie, that he would not part with His Title to thoſe counties and lands; and that the Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Engliſh Proteſtants might proceed as was formerly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: But when thoſe miſchievous Councells, (now onely prevalent with His Majeſtie) found that the Parliament had both diſcovered and interrupted them in ſome meaſure, and that their Deſigne could be no longer carryed on by fraud and ſubtilties, as before; and had therefore projected this hideous Rebellion, then the Lord <hi>Gormanſtown,</hi> Sir <hi>Donnaugh Mac
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132705:5"/> Carthy</hi> Knight, now Lord Viſcount <hi>Muſkerry. Nicholas Plunket,</hi> Uncle to the Earl of <hi>Fingal,</hi> Sir <hi>Roe-buck Lynch,</hi> and <hi>Jeffery Brown</hi> a Lawyer (all principall and active Rebels now in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>) and <hi>Thomas Bourke</hi> (who was named a Commſſioner in the late Commiſſion to Treat with the Rebels, and whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, brothers, and kindred are all now in Rebellion, being the chief of the Popiſh part of that Iriſh Committee: were conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and careſſed at Whitehall, and they or ſome of them without the privity of the reſt of that Committee, had divers private conferrences with the King in the <hi>Queens</hi> preſence: and what Clandeſtine agreement was made with thoſe Rebels may eaſily be imagined, when upon their private mediation His Majeſty was induced to give away theſe five whole Counties, with a great part of the Counties of <hi>Limerick</hi> and <hi>Tipperary;</hi> after ſo great an endeavour had bin uſed for divers yeers together, to entitle His Majeſty to the ſame; and all this for a rent of 2000. l. or thereabouts, when as in finding the Offices, ſearching Records and admeaſuring theſe Counties, and Lands the King had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended out of His Own Coffers ten thouſand pounds and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. And this ſervice of entitling the King was before that time eſteemed ſuch a Maſter-piece of the ſaid Earle, that ſome perſons who came over to complaine againſt the Earle for the ſame were impriſoned here, and after ſent into <hi>Ireland</hi> to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dealt with as the ſaid Earle ſhould think fit.</p>
            <p>Neither is it improper to obſerve upon this occaſion, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream difference between this Superlative Indulgence to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Papiſts, by this unuſuall bounty, and that exquiſite piece of injuſtice offered to the City of <hi>London,</hi> in the caſe of <hi>London Derry</hi> and <hi>Collerane;</hi> which ſhews the Land of <hi>Ireland</hi> is worth the owning, where no greater compenſation is propoſed for the parting therewith: And His Majeſty was drawn to tell the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for <hi>Ireland,</hi> that now ſince he was content to part with ſo much of His Right, He expected they would recompence Him ſome other way.</p>
            <p>Immediately after, (namely in Auguſt before the Rebellion) they returned into <hi>Ireland,</hi> where how they beſtir'd themſelves by ſeconding their Letters and Meſſages, with their perſonall ſollicitations, did appear by the Sequele for that the 23. of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber following, this Rebellion brake forth in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe violent preſumptions may be added, that which is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132705:5"/> expreſly proved by <hi>Archdeacon Maxwell,</hi> a Learned Divine, who teſtifies in his Examinations taken in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that he heard <hi>Tirlagh Oge O Neile,</hi> brother to Sir <hi>Phelim O Neale,</hi> the arch Rebell of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> confeſſe; That this buſineſſe (meaning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion) was communicated by the Popiſh Iriſh Committee to the Papiſts in <hi>England,</hi> who promiſed their aſſiſtance, and that by their advice, ſomething formerly reſolved on were altered; ſaying, it was a good omen and undoubted ſigne of divine appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, that the Parliament of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould ſend over a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee into <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>major</hi> part whereof were Papiſts. And <hi>Mac Mahoun</hi> who was to joyn with the Lord <hi>MacGuire</hi> for the ſurprizing the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin:</hi> being taken and examined at the Racke, confeſſed that the originall of that Rebellion was brought to them out of <hi>England</hi> by the Iriſh Committee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to His Majeſty for redreſſe of Grievances, as by the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Fol. 2</note> of <hi>James Pieſly</hi> Gentleman, herewith Printed may appeare.</p>
            <p>And as theſe Iriſh Papiſts did negotiate in both Kingdomes, ſo the Earl of <hi>Caſtlehaven,</hi> a Peer of this Realm; (that ſate here in Parliament at the beginning thereof, but now a notorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell in <hi>Ireland</hi>) Mr. <hi>Porter,</hi> ſon to <hi>Endimion Porter,</hi> who decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe a Papiſt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Sir <hi>Bazill Brooke,</hi> the Popiſh Treaſurer for the moneys raiſed by the Queens ſollicitation for the War againſt the Scots; Mr. <hi>Andrew Brown</hi> a Lawyer of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colns-Inne,</hi> heretofore expelled thence for being a knowne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, with divers other dangerous Engliſh Papiſts went out of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Summer before the Rebellion brake forth, and were very active there.</p>
            <p>If theſe Circumſtances preceding the Rebellion, and divers other of the like nature, be not enough of themſelves to open the eyes of the world, It hath pleaſed God to diſcover ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent evidence of this kind, that may ſerve to convince the greateſt unbeliever. Therefore (not repeating any of the proofs ſet forth in that Anſwer to His Majeſties Meſſage of the 13th. of Auguſt, 1642. but referring to the ſame herewith printed to which no Reply hath yet been made;) they think fit to adde to that evidence this which followes, namely the generall profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Rebells in all parts of that Kingdome, that the cauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132705:6"/> of their riſing was to preſerve His Majeſty and the Queen, from being oppreſt by the Puritan-Parliament, and that it was by their conſent. That they knew well the beſt in <hi>England</hi> would<note place="margin">Colonell <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin's</hi> Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. <hi>See</hi> Folio 33. <hi>William Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art</hi> Eſq's; Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. <hi>See</hi> Folio 36. <hi>Hen: Steuart's</hi> Examination. <hi>See</hi> Fol. 37.</note> ſide with them, that they had good Warrant in black and white for what they did. Their calling the Engliſh Army Parliament-Rogues, and Traitors to the Queen: and telling them at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Rebellion before any appearance of War here, that ere long they ſhould ſee <hi>England</hi> as much in blood as <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> then was. That they had their party in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which ſhould keep both Kingdomes ſo buſie at home, that they ſhould not ſend any ayd againſt them, with a multitude of ſuch like expreſſions from the Iriſh of the beſt quality and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; as may appear by the Examinations of Colonell <hi>Audley Mervin, William Steuart,</hi> Eſquire, <hi>William-Steuart,</hi> Cent' here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with printed, and by divers other proofs. And although theſe expreſſions proceed from Rebels, yet concurring with a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of other proofs, and found true in a great part by ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience are not inconſiderable.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Moneth of October wherein the Rebellion of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> brake forth; the Lord <hi>Dillon</hi> of Coſtelough, (an Iriſh Peer, now in armes againſt the Parliament and Kingdom of <hi>England</hi>) went out of Scotland from His Majeſty into <hi>Ireland,</hi> bringing His Majeſties Letters (which he obtained by mediation of the Queeen) to be preſently ſworne a Privie-Councellor of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who when he had taken the Oath of a Privie. Councellor, endeavours to be uſefull to the Rebells, preſents to the Lords, Juſtices, and Councell, from many of the Centry and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the County of <hi>Longford,</hi> (all in Rebellion) a rebellious and ſcandalous Letter in the nature of a Remonſtrance, full of pretended grievances and unreaſonable demands: As namely, to have freedom of Religion, a repeall of all Laws made to the contrary, and the like; as by the ſaid Letter herewith printed may appeare.</p>
            <p>In December after the Rebellion, the ſame Lord <hi>Dillon,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his brother in Law, the now Lord <hi>Taaffe,</hi> (a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Papiſt) repaired into <hi>England,</hi> bringing with them ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Papers and Inſtructions in writing from the Lord <hi>Gorman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> and other Lords and Gentlemen of the <hi>Pale,</hi> all now in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:132705:6"/> to negotiate for them to His Majeſty, and as they ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite with His Majeſty here on the behalf of the Rebels, ſo doe they ſollicite the Rebels from hence in the Name of His Majeſty, to perſiſt in their wicked Rebellion, as appears by the Teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Jephſon,</hi> a Member of the Houſe of Commons, lately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered at a Conference before both Houſes in theſe words. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>AT my late being at</hi> Oxford, <hi>finding the Lord</hi> Dillon <hi>and the Lord</hi> Taaffe <hi>in favour at Court, I acquainted the Lord</hi> Faulk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>His Majeſties Secretary, that there were two Lords about the King, who to His Majeſties great diſhonour, and the great diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of His good Subjects, did make uſe of His Majeſties Name to incourage the Rebells; to make this appeare, I informed that I had ſeen two Letters ſent by the Lord</hi> Dillon <hi>and the Lord</hi> Taaffe, <hi>to the Lord of</hi> Muskerie, <hi>the chief man in Rebellion in Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and one of the Iriſh Committee ſent into England; intimating that though it did not ſtand with the conveniency of His Maieſties Affaires to give him publique countenance, yet that his Majeſty was well pleaſed with what he did, and would in time give him thankes for it; (or neer to that purpoſe) That theſe Letters were ſeen by the Lord</hi> Inchiquine, <hi>the chief Commander of the Engliſh Forces in Mounſter, and by his Secretary who had kept Copies of them; and that I was ready to juſtifie as much. Whereupon the Lo:</hi> Faulkland, <hi>was pleaſed to ſay, that they deſerved to be hanged. But though I ſtayed there at</hi> Oxford <hi>about a week after this diſcovery made; I never was called to any farther accompt, nor any prejudice done to theſe two Lords, but they had the ſame freedome in Court as before for ought I could obſerve or hear to the contrary,</hi>
               </q> Thus far in Mr. <hi>Jephſons</hi> owne language, a man of knowne honour and integrity.</p>
            <p>That ſince this diſcovery made to the Lord <hi>Faulkland</hi> by Mr. <hi>Jephſon,</hi> the ſame Lord <hi>Taaffe,</hi> one <hi>Roche,</hi> and <hi>William Brent,</hi> a Lawyer, active Papiſts, with Letters from His Majeſty went from <hi>Oxford</hi> to <hi>Dublin:</hi> And upon Thurſday before Whitſuntide 1643. in the Evening (taking with them one Colonell <hi>Barry,</hi> a proteſt Papiſt) and pretending for <hi>Connaught</hi> ſlipt away to <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> where the Tueſday following was a generall aſſembly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132705:7"/> of all the chief Rebels. When they had done their Errand, <hi>Barry</hi> was left Lieger at KILKENNY among the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels; the Lord <hi>Taaffe</hi> returned to DUBLIN, and upon Friday the 9. of <hi>June,</hi> 1643. the Lord <hi>Taaffe</hi> with divers of the Privie-Councell of Ireland, that favour the Rebels, met at the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond's</hi> houſe, where the Propoſitions which the Lord <hi>Taaffe</hi> brought from the Rebels were debated. The Lord <hi>Taaffe</hi> is ſince gone into Cannaught, <hi>Brent</hi> is come back to <hi>Oxford</hi> to give an accompt of this imployment.</p>
            <p>By this which hath bin thus truely related, every man may conſtrue what was meant by His Majeſties not conſenting that the Parliament ſhould ſend a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittee into <hi>Ireland</hi> the laſt yeer, to endeavour the carrying on the War againſt the Rebels, upon pretence that the Earl of <hi>Lieceſter</hi> was preſently to go over thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who is yet remaining at <hi>Oxford.</hi> That when that Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee had prevailed with the Lords-Iuſtices and Councell, and with many of the prime Commanders and other Officers of the Army in <hi>Leinſter,</hi> to ſubſcribe by way of Adventure for Land in <hi>Ireland</hi> to be ſetled by a new Bill, very conſiderable ſums which were to be deducted out of their reſpective entertainments, and were in a fair and hopefull way to induce moſt of the Officers of that Kingdome to do the like, which would have been a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall meanes under God to have quickned the mannaging of that Warr, when the Officers that muſt do the worke ſhould have bin engaged in intereſt, as well as honour to proſecute the ſame with vigour and effect and would have leſſened the inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable charge of that War, and in all probability would have encouraged the Adventurers in <hi>London</hi> and elſewhere, to have proceeded cheerfully to a ſecond Subſcription. Then to render this endeavour fruitleſſe, one Captain <hi>Yarner</hi> did confidently affirm, that thoſe which had or ſhould ſubſcribe, were enemies to the King, a thing ſo incredible, that few could believe it, till the ſame man went to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and upon his returne to <hi>Dublin,</hi> aſſured the Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> and the Officers, that he had diſcourſed with His Majeſty about this way of Subſcription, and that His Majeſty did not approve of the ſame: Whereupon thoſe who had ſubſcribed did withdraw their hands, and the reſt were wholly diſcouraged, finding His Majeſty to diſlike of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132705:7"/> that way, which he had formerly approved of, by His Aſſent to the Propoſitions preſented to Him at <hi>Dover;</hi> and by His Royall Aſſent to foure Acts of Parliament, all made in purſuance of theſe Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>That about this time a Commiſſion was ſent over, to meet with the Rebells, and to hear what they could ſay or propound for themſelves, which Commiſſion was directed to the Lord Marqueſſe <hi>Ormond,</hi> the Commander in chief of the Engliſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies there, (whoſe duty was to fight, and not to treat with the Rebells;) and to ſome other Commiſſioners, among whom the ſaid <hi>Thomas Bourk</hi> that had an hand in contriving this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, was one, and who brought the ſaid Commiſſion into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and confidently delivered the ſame at the Councell Table, to the amazement of all the Councell then preſent that were not acquainted with the Plot.</p>
            <p>And whereas by an Act of Parliament it is provided, <hi>That all the Monies paid in upon that Act, ſhall be imployed for the ſpeedy and effectuall ſubduing of the ſaid Rebels, by ſending over into the ſaid Realm of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and diſpoſing there ſuch forces of foot &amp; horſe, Monies, Ammunition, Victuall, and all other things neceſſary for a war, in ſuch manner as the Lords and Commons in Parliament ſhall from time to time direct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas the Lords and Commons finding that from the Battell of <hi>Kilruſh,</hi> which was fought in <hi>April,</hi> 1642. till <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> following, the Army in <hi>Leinſter</hi> had not been ſo active as was expected; and therefore to quicken the War, to inform themſelves of the wants and defects of the Army, and of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things that might enable them the better, <hi>To ſend thither, and diſpoſe of there, (according to that Statute) ſuch Forces, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Ammunition and Neceſſaries,</hi> as were requiſite for that ſervice, thought it very expedient to ſend into <hi>Ireland</hi> a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for that purpoſe, Members of the Houſe of Commons, but authoriſed from both Houſes, who carrying with them above Twenty thouſand pounds in ready Money, beſides great ſtore of Powder, Match, and other Ammunition, and hazarding their lives in the Winter ſeaſon, meerly for the good of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, might juſtly have expected a cordiall welcome there. But when thoſe that now appear too evidently to favour the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132705:8"/> ſaw that during the abode of the Committee there, Parties were continually ſent forth to deſtroy the Enemy: That the Committee engaged their own particular credits, to take up Monies for the relief, and ſetting forth of the Army; That the Commiſſion ſent over to treat with the Rebels, was not like to have ſo good ſucceſſe as was wiſhed by them, ſo long as the Committee were preſent at the Councell-Table, where all the proceedings againſt the Rebells were promoted and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; A Letter was ſent from His Majeſty to the Lords Iuſtices and Councell to this effect, that His Majeſtie took notice, that without His conſent or privity, they had admitted of one Maſter <hi>Robert Goodwyn,</hi> and one Maſter <hi>Reynolds,</hi> to be preſent at their debates, who thereupon were become ſo bold, as to Vote with them, a thing of ſuch preſumption, as none of their predeceſſors would have done or ſuffered: And therefore His Majeſty did require the Lords Iuſtices and Councell, not to admit them any more; That He knew of no buſineſſe thoſe men had in His Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> but if they had any, they ſhould make their addreſſes like other of His Subjects; and did upon their Allegiance charge the Lords Iuſtices and Councell to take care that thoſe perſons did not ſow Sedition among His good Subjects. And 'tis obſervable that this Letter (like that which accompanyed the Commiſſion to treat with the Rebells) was only ſigned with His Majeſties hand, without any Secretaries hand to avow the ſame. That it was brought over by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> his own Secretary, who was ſent very ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Oxford</hi> a little before. That although both Houſes before the ſending over of their Committee had acquainted His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty therewith by Letter, and ſent him a Copy of the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which they had given to their Committees, to which Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Inſtructions, an Anſwer was returned by Sir <hi>Edward Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> as from His Majeſty acknowledging thereby that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions were the ſame in effect which His Majeſty had given to the Earle of <hi>Lieceſter;</hi> Yet after all this, His Majeſty was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſay in that Letter, that He knew of no buſineſſe thoſe men had in His Kingdom of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tis further obſervable that a Committee ſent by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of both Houſes of Parliament, (who had both the charge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:132705:8"/> and mannaging of the War referred unto them;) to negotiate and conſult with a State in diſtreſſe for their own good, where every Privy-Councellor ſate covered in Counſell, there ſuch a Committee ſo qualified ſhould make their addreſſes like other of His Majeſties Subjects: That is to ſay, ſhould ſtand bare-hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the back of the Councell day by day, from morning to night, <hi>and humbly beſeech them to ſave the Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and conſequently their own eſtates, at the proper coſt and charges of the Parliament and Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>who ſent them thither.</hi> Laſtly, the Commons cannot conceive what is meant that the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices and Councell, are ſtraightly charg'd in that Letter upon their Allegiance, not to ſuffer the Committee to ſow Sedition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong His Majeſties good Subjects, unleſſe to ſtir up and incite the Engliſh Souldiers in the pay of the Parliament, to proceed vigorouſly againſt thoſe bloody Iriſh Rebels; be conſtrued as a ſowing of Sedition among His Majeſties good Subjects; for that the Iriſh Rebels ſhould be now eſteemed his Majeſties good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, is more then probable by that which followes. Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Brereton</hi> Knight of the Shire for the County of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> a man of honour and Religion, by his Letter to the Speaker of the Houſe of Commons, dated from <hi>Liverpoole</hi> in Lancaſhire the 7. of June, 1643. and herewith likewiſe printed. After ſome account given of his happy proceedings in thoſe parts, writes in this manner. Within few dayes after this Victory there landed out of two Barques many Iriſh Rebels, in <hi>Werrall</hi> in Cheſhire, ſome whereof acknowledged in the preſence of divers ſufficient men, who affirmed the ſame unto me; that they had waſhed their hands in the blood of divers Engliſh and Scots in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and now hoped to waſh their hands in the bloud of Engliſh men in <hi>England;</hi> which Rebels being brought unto <hi>Cheſter,</hi> were accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſeverall of thoſe poor Engliſh who fled from <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>Cheſter</hi> for refuge, to bee the perſons who cut their husbands throats, others that they ripped up their childrens bowels. The Country wherein they firſt arrived did apprehend ſo much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſt, that they did all riſe with their beſt weapons, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended divers of the Iriſh Rebels, but being unarmed, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paſt ſeven or eight Musketteers they could not make good their priſoners, who were reſcued out of their hands by a Troop
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132705:9"/> of Horſe which came from the Commiſſioners of Array, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſeized about 28 of our honeſt Country men priſoners. Theſe Iriſh acknowledge they caome from <hi>Strangford,</hi> and that there are<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Willi Breretons</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Fol. 41</note> 1200. ſome ſpeake of 1000. more to follow after, as by the ſaid Letter herewich printed may appear.</p>
            <p>So theſe Iriſh Rebels were taken for good Subjects, and ſet at liberty, and the honeſt men that had taken them impriſoned in their ſtead.</p>
            <p>And that the Counſells now predominant at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the ſupreame Councell of Rebels at <hi>Kilkenny</hi> are equally His Majeſties good Subjects, and do ayme at one and the ſame thing, and are concurring and ayding one another as well by Sea as by Land, is apparent by that which followes.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners authoriſed to command the Kings Forces in the Weſt, (<hi>viz.</hi>) The Lord <hi>Mohun,</hi> Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> and others, by an authority derived unto them under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> as they expreſſe themſelves; do grant Commiſſions or Letters of Mart, for the apprehending, ſeizing, and taking for His Majeſties Service, all Ships and Veſſells, belonging to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Towns, and Ports of <hi>London, Exeter, Hull, Portſmouth, Dart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, Barnſtable, Biddeford</hi> &amp; <hi>Plymouth,</hi> or belonging to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cities, Towns, or Ports of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. As by a Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion; or Letters of Mart, bearing date the firſt of June, 1643.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Letter Mart. Fol. 44.</note> under the hands and ſeales of the Lord <hi>Mohun,</hi> Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Barklay,</hi> herewith likewiſe printed may appear.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide the Rebels of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the name of the ſupream Councell of the confederate Catholiques of <hi>Ireland,</hi> do grant Commiſſions or Letters of Mart, for the taking of all His Majeſties Enemies, and the enemies of the generall Catholique cauſe now in hand in that Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as by a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion dated the 5. of March, 1642. granted by the ſaid Supreame Councell, to one <hi>Francis Oliver</hi> a Flemming, herewith likewiſe<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>er of Mart. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>0. 46.</note> printed may appear.</p>
            <p>And as the Ships in His Majeſties ſervice do gratifie the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in ſeizing the Ships that bring proviſion for the relief of the Engliſh Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as appears by the Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>John Davice,</hi> Eſquire, Commiſſary of Victuall for the Province of ULSTER; Who teſtifieth as followeth</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:132705:9"/>
            <p>That a Ship called <hi>The Michael of London,</hi> whereof <hi>Sydrake Pope</hi> was Maſter, was ſent for <hi>France</hi> by the ſaid <hi>John Davice,</hi> with 648 Hydes, which were to be ſold, and converted into Corn, for the relief of the Army in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter:</hi> This Ship, by foul weather in <hi>December,</hi> 1642. was forced into <hi>Falmouth</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> where ſhe was ſeized on by Sir <hi>Nich. Slanning,</hi> and by him ſent into <hi>France,</hi> and the proceed of the Hydes return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him in the ſaid Ship, in Powder, Match, and Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. That about the 20 of <hi>April,</hi> 1643. a Ship belonging to<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of M.</hi> Davice, <hi>Fol. 48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>William King</hi> of <hi>Dover,</hi> laden with Wines and Salt from <hi>France,</hi> and bound for <hi>Carrigfergus</hi> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> upon the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the ſaid <hi>John Davice,</hi> was taken at Sea by one <hi>Rich. Jones,</hi> Captain of a Ship ſet out from <hi>Falmouth</hi> by His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Warrant; and as well the Ship, as the Goods, were ſold at <hi>Brest</hi> in <hi>France</hi> by the ſaid <hi>Jones.</hi> So the Rebells of <hi>Ireland</hi> do in like manner gratifie His Majeſty, by commanding the Ships ſet forth by them to examine all Engliſh ſhips at Sea, Whether they be for the King or Parliament: and if they be for the King, to let them go; but if for the Parliament, to take and pillage them; as may appear by the Examinations of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See their Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, fol.</hi> 49, &amp; 50.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtopher Haſſall,</hi> and <hi>Marke Roche,</hi> two Iriſh Sea-men of <hi>Wixford</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who were taken upon the Coaſt of <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and <hi>June</hi> 12, 1643. examined before the head Officers of <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> and authentique Copies of thoſe Examinations ſent up to the Houſe of Commons, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Printed.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Antrim,</hi> a notorious Rebell, was taken by the Scots Army in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and impriſoned there, upon ſuſpition of High Treaſon: to avoid his Tryall, he brake Priſon, and fled into the North parts of <hi>England,</hi> and hath been with the Queen at <hi>Yorke</hi> a long time; from whence he was ſent to the Rebels of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> with ſecret Inſtructions, and had Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aſſigned him by the Queens directions: And what care was taken of his Ammunition, will appear by a Letter dated at <hi>Yorke</hi> the 8 of <hi>May,</hi> 1643. written by Serjeant-Major <hi>Roſſe,</hi> to that <hi>Apoſtata</hi> Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley,</hi> Governour of <hi>Scarbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> intercepted by the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and ſent up to the Houſe of Commons; wherein <hi>Cholmley</hi> is intreated to have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:132705:10"/> ſuch care of the Ammunition appertaining to the Lord of <hi>Aboyn,</hi> as he ſhall have of the Lord of <hi>Antrims</hi> Ammunition, for M. <hi>Jermin</hi> hath deſired him to write theſe lines; as by the Letter herewith alſo Printed may appear; and what relation M.<note place="margin">See the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Fol. 51.</note> 
               <hi>Jermin</hi> hath to the Qu: is well known to the world. Since this care taken of the Ammunition of the Earl of <hi>Antrim,</hi> and the L. of <hi>Aboyn,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi> is taken the ſecond time by Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Major <hi>Monroe,</hi> in the County of <hi>Downe</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as he was returning from the Queen to the Rebells of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> with divers Letters, Inſtructions, and Papers: and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Depoſition of the Earl of <hi>Antrim's</hi> own ſervant (who was taken with his Maſter, and ſince condemned and executed) it is evident that there was, and doubtleſſe yet is, an impious Deſigne on foot to reconcile the Engliſh and Iriſh in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp; that by their joynt power having expelled the Scots, the Iriſh Forces there might be ſent againſt the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> The Earl of <hi>Antrim,</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Aboyn,</hi> (whoſe Arms aſſigned them by the Queen for this purpoſe were taken care of by M. <hi>Jermyn</hi>) as appears by the ſaid Letter from Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant Major <hi>Roſſe</hi>) and the Earl of <hi>Niddiſdale,</hi> were three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Agents employed in this horrid Plot: And that it may cleerly appear to the whole world from whence all our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and calamities do proceed, the ſame Lord of <hi>Aboyn,</hi> by his Letter directed to the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi> then with the Queen,<note place="margin">See the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the 8 of May, 1643. Fol. 54.</note> bearing Date at <hi>Caerliſle</hi> the 8 of <hi>May,</hi> 1643. and taken in the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi> his pockets, among the reſt of the Letters and Papers, writes in theſe words; <hi>My Lord, being certainly informed by</hi> Niddiſdale's <hi>ſervant, That there is a new Order ſince we parted, for ſtopping of the Ammunition, I have taken occaſion to intreat your Lordſhip by this Bearer, that I may know the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of it. I muſt confeſſe, it ſurprizeth me, that any diſtance ſhould alter ſo ſeaſonable a concluſion: and certainly I ſhall never deſerve to be made the Inſtrument of fruſtrating the hopes of their parts which ſhould have been enabled by this Supply; I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded there is ſcarce another mean to make our fidelity</hi> uſeleſſe for Her Majeſties Service: And laſtly, deſires the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi> in that Letter, to acquaint <hi>the Queen</hi> with theſe effects of his ingenuity, as by the ſaid Letter herewith likewiſe Printed may
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:132705:10"/> appear. And that it might appear to the Rebels of <hi>Ireland</hi> that the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi> was accounted His Majeſties good Subject, and had His Majeſties approbation for what he was to act there, he was furniſhed with a Paſſe from the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> in theſe words; </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="pass">
               <body>
                  <p>WILLIAM <hi>Earl of Newcaſtle, Governour of the Town and County of Newcaſtle, and Generall of all His Majeſties Forces raiſed in the Northern parts of this Kingdom, for defence of the ſame: To all Coloncls, Lievtenant-Coloncls, Serjeant Majors, Captains, and all other His Majeſties loving Subjects of England and Ireland. For aſ much as the Right Honourable the Earl of Antrim is to travell to Dublin in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and other parts of that Kingdom, Theſe are therefore to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and require you, and every of you, to whom this ſhall come to be ſeen, to permit him and his ſervants quietly and peaceably to paſſe and repaſſe into thoſe parts, and back again, without any moleſtation or interruption: And further I do hereby require all Poſt-maſters, Conſtables, and other Officers, to furniſh the ſaid Earl and his ſervants with ſo many Poſt-horſes as they ſhall have need of from place to place, and ſtage to ſtage for all the ſaid Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See this Paſſe, Fol. 55.</note> 
                     <hi>he and they paying the uſuall Rates for the ſam. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you, or any of you may not fail at your perill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <date>Given under mine Hand and Seal, the 4 day of <hi>May,</hi> 1643.</date>
                     <signed>Signed, <hi>William Newcaſtle.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Neither can it be imagined that the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> a Privy Councellor, and a great Commander under His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, durſt have adventured to have given ſuch a Paſſe to ſo notorious a Rebell, without expreſſe Warrant ſo to do: which Paſſe, together with the ſaid Letters, were found in the Earl of <hi>Antrim,</hi> pockets, and were ſent by Major Generall <hi>Monroe</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> from whence authentique Copies are ſent hither, which are likewiſe herewith Printed, together<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration from</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>of the 9 of Iune, 1643. Fol. 56.</hi>
               </note> with a Declaration of the Lords of His Majeſties Privie Councell in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Commiſſioners, for conſerving the Articles of the Treaty, dated at <hi>Edingburgh</hi> the 9 of <hi>June</hi> 1643, concerning the apprehending and employment of the Earl of <hi>Antrim,</hi> with their ſenſe upon the ſame; As alſo a Letter ſent from Major Generall <hi>Monroe</hi> (who took the ſaid Earl of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trim</hi>) to the Committee appointed by the Houſe of Commons
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:132705:11"/> for the affairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> bearing date at <hi>Carrick fergus</hi> the 23<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Generall Major</hi> Monroe <hi>his Letter. Fol. 60.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>May,</hi> 1643: To which may be added the Earl of <hi>Antrim's</hi> own confeſſion, who was examined before Major Generall <hi>Monroe</hi> and a Counſell of War, the 12. of June 1643. and in his examination confeſſes that he came into <hi>Ireland</hi> with the Lord of <hi>Newcaſtles</hi> Paſſe, and with private Inſtructions for making of Peace; and Maſter <hi>Steuart</hi> another ſervant of the ſaid Earl of <hi>Antrim,</hi> and taken with him, being likewiſe exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the ſaid 12. of June 1643. before the ſaid Generall <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roc</hi> and Councell of War, and threatned with torture except he would declare by whoſe Warrant and direction the ſaid Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi> had undertaken that imployment, ſaith, That as the Ammunition and Arms was to be furniſhed by the Queens Order and Command; So that he doubts not but the Earl of <hi>Antrims</hi> imployment and others was directed by her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie.</p>
            <p>But yet to come neerer home, The Houſe of Commons among a numerous company of Proofs of this kinde, too many to be all related, ſhall conclude with the teſtimony of <hi>John Dod,</hi> late Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Annegilliffe,</hi> in the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi> in the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who was examined at the Bar of the Houſe of Commons, and after before a ſelect Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the ſaid Houſe, and teſtifieth that after he had ſuffered many miſeries in this Rebellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> he repaired into this Kingdom, and ſome occaſions carrying him to <hi>Oxford,</hi> he ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there ſeven weeks, and came out of <hi>Oxford</hi> the 13 of June 1643. That during his ſtay there he ſaw a great number of Iriſh Rebells, whom he very well knew to have had an hand in the moſt barbarous actions of that Rebellion, as the daſhing of ſmall Infants in pieces, the ripping up of women with childe, and the like, among whom was one <hi>Thomas Bradye,</hi> who at <hi>Turbet</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> within 7 miles where the ſaid <hi>Dod</hi> lived; as 36 old men, women, and children, not able to flee, were paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing over a Bridge, cauſed them all to be thrown into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where they were all drowned; that this <hi>Brady</hi> is now at <hi>Oxford</hi> in great favour, and Serjeant Major to Colonell <hi>Piercie</hi> his Regiment; that he ſaw there 3 Franciſcan Friers, namely, <hi>Bryan ô Gormuly, Anthony mac Geochagan,</hi> and <hi>Thomus Nugent;</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:132705:11"/> and 3 Jeſuites, namely, <hi>Lawrence Sutton, Philip Roch,</hi> and <hi>Edmund ô Rely,</hi> who were all very earneſt for the Cauſe, and daily encouraging the Souldiers to ſight againſt the <hi>Round-heads,</hi> and for that purpoſe have liſted themſelves in the Lord <hi>Dillons</hi> Troop, as was affirmed by divers; they go very brave and are called Cornetts; That there are daily and publique meetings at Maſſe, in almoſt every ſtreet there, and verily beleeves in his conſcience, that for one Sermon Preached there, are 4 Maſſes ſaid now at <hi>Oxford;</hi> That he ſaw Sir <hi>John Dungan</hi> there, a man accuſed of high Treaſon in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for being in the Rebellion, and fled into <hi>England,</hi> who hath a Commiſſion for a Troop of Horſe; The Lord <hi>Barnewall</hi> of <hi>Trimleſtowne,</hi> and his ſon, who hath a Commiſſion for a Troop of Horſe, and is now gone into <hi>Wales</hi> to raiſe them; A ſon of the Lord <hi>Newterfield,</hi> who hath gotten a Command likewiſe; that as neer as he can poſſibly compute, there was then at <hi>Oxford</hi> above 3000 Rebels; and that moſt of the Kings Life-guard are Iriſh; by all which it may appear that the Iriſh Rebels are not onely eſteemed His<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of</hi> Mr <hi>Dod. fol. 62.</hi>
               </note> Majeſties good Subjects, but even the beſt of His Subjects, when they are thus admitted ſo neer His Majeſties own perſon.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole matter, no man can think that this Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo barbarous and bloody, that one hundred and fifty four thouſand Proteſtants, men, women, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Engliſh and Scotch, were Maſſacred in that Kingdom, between the 23 of October, when the Rebellion brake forth, and the firſt of March following, by the computation of the Prieſts themſelves that were preſent, and principall Actors in all thoſe Tragedies, and were directed by ſome chief Rebells of <hi>Ireland</hi> to take this computation, leſt they ſhould be reported to be more bloody then in truth there was cauſe, all which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the examination of the ſaid Arch-deacon <hi>Maxwell,</hi> who lived as a Priſoner a long time with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Phelmi O Neils</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and was there when this Computation was brought in.</p>
            <p>No man can beleeve that this horrid and unparareld Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion ſhould be the undertaking of the Rebels alone, being ſet on foot when a Parliament was ſitting in <hi>England</hi> that could
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:132705:12"/> not diſſolve without its own conſent, when all Nations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Romiſh Religion were at peace with <hi>England,</hi> and ſo engaged at home, that the Rebells in reaſon could not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any conſiderable aſſiſtance from them, nor could think themſelves able to incounter <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> either; much leſſe both together, being ſo concerned and engaged by Religion, and the common intereſt of both Kingdoms, to ſuppreſſe by all means poſſible, ſo inſufferable an inſurrection: So that to imagine the Nobility, Gentry, and in a manner, the whole Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who at that time enjoyed more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Religion, then they had done for many yeers before; ſhould thus deſperately engage their lives and eſtates in ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſo raſh an enterpriſe, without being encouraged, incited, nay commanded from <hi>England,</hi> with an aſſurance both of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence and aſſiſtance too, were to deny them to be reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Creatures.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Houſe of Commons abundantly ſatisfied in their own conſciences and judgements of the trueth hereof, (though with deep ſorrow and amazement) cannot but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the world, That by all theſe concurring circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and convincing Proofs, (to which nothing can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſave a witneſſe, to confeſſe that he was preſent at the making of the bargain, which no man will expect in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie of this horrid and high importance) that this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of and monſtrous Rebellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> was project<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, incited, and aſſiſted, by thoſe Councells now onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent with His Majeſtie. That the Queen with her Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Prieſts, the Papiſts of all His Majeſties three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, have been principall Actours and Sticklers herein. That now thoſe bloody Rebels have, in a manner, rooted out the Proteſtant Religion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> there is a Deſigne to pardon them, and to bring them into <hi>England</hi> to do the like. That no earthly power is likely in humane reaſon to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this damnable Plot, but the power of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> which is now declared by a late Proclamation to be no free Parliament, to be null, and of none effect: and all poſſible endeavour uſed by ſtrength and ſtratagem to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:132705:12"/> the ſame. So that unleſſe the Royall blood of King <hi>James,</hi> and the innocent blood of the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> do lie as a crying and ſtupendious guilt upon this Nation; which God hath determined at this time to revenge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talliate: the Houſe of Commons do conceive it impoſſible, that ſo many of thoſe which would be thought the honeſt and moderate Engliſh Proteſtants, ſhould any longer be blinded and led on, to joyn with German, French, Wallon, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, Scotch, and Iriſh Papiſts; and thereby to ſurrender up at once, The Proteſtant Religion, The Parliament, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> into the hands of Papiſts and Strangers; that ſo this Renowned Kingdom may be no more a Nation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:132705:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Proteſtation of the Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops of <hi>Ireland,</hi> againſt the toleration of Popery, agreed upon, and ſubſcribed by them at <hi>Dublin</hi> November 26. 1626.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Religion</hi> of the Papiſts is <hi>Superſtitious</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> their <hi>Faith</hi> and Doctrine <hi>erroneous</hi> and Hereticall; Their <hi>Church,</hi> in reſpect of both, <hi>Apoſtaticall.</hi> To give them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>Toleration,</hi> or to conſent that they may freely exerciſe their <hi>Religion,</hi> and confeſſe their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> is a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſin: and that in two reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is to make our ſelves acceſſary, not onely to their <hi>Superſtitions, Idolatries, Hereſies;</hi> and in a word, to all the abominations of <hi>Popery;</hi> but alſo (which is a conſequence of the former) to the Perdition of the ſeduced people, which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the deluge of their <hi>Catholique Apoſtaſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, To grant them a <hi>Toleration</hi> in reſpect of any Money to be given, or contribution to be made by them, is to ſet Religion to ſale, and withall, the ſouls of the people, whom <hi>Chriſt our Saviour</hi> hath redeemed with his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood.</p>
            <p>And as it is a great Sin, ſo it is a matter of moſt dangerous conſequence; the conſideration whereof we leave to the wiſe and judicious: beſeeching the <hi>jealous God of Trueth</hi> to make all thoſe who are in <hi>Authority</hi> zealous of <hi>Gods glory,</hi> and the advancement of true <hi>Religion,</hi> and reſolute and couragious againſt all <hi>Popery, Superstition,</hi> and <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="affidavit">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:132705:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>James Peiſley,</hi> late of <hi>Dublin,</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Saith,</opener>
            <p>THat about the moneth of March 1641. it was his fortune to be preſent when <hi>Mackmaghon,</hi> one of the grand Rebels of <hi>Ireland,</hi> was Wracked, and his Examination taken by Sir <hi>Charles Coot, ſenior:</hi> in the preſence of Sir <hi>Francis Willowby,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Loſters,</hi> the Conſtable of the Caſtle, and ſome others, the ſaid <hi>Mackmohon</hi> confeſſed that the Originall of that Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion was brought over to them by their Committee, who were imployed by the Iriſh Parliament to His Majeſtie, for redreſſe of their Grievances in that Kingdom, and that they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving often ſolicited His Majeſtie for that purpoſe, was anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That he was willing to grant them their deſire, and that he did confeſſe they were His good Subjects; but that He was ſo oppreſt by his Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> that he knew not how to relieve them; wiſhing he knew how to be revenged on them, or words to that purpoſe; which occaſioned Sir <hi>Charles Coot</hi> to take him up, calling him Rogue and Raskall, for offering to lay ſuch a charge upon the King, whom he ſaid would aſſiſt them in things honeſt and juſt, but not give them Commiſſion to cut our Throats. This Narration was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed in the Examination read to <hi>Mackmaghon</hi> after S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Charles Coot</hi> had finiſhed it: The Reaſon, as this Examinate then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, was, That it being a matter of great conſequence, they would take ſome other time to examine that point more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, which whether they did or no, this Examinae knows not.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:132705:14"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the Commons aſſembled in PARLIAMENT: In Anſwer to His Majeſties Meſſage of the 13 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1642. ſhewing the obſtructions of the relief of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Houſe of Commons having received a Meſſage from His Majeſty of the 13 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are required to retract an Order made by them for the borrowing of One hundred thouſand pounds of the Adventurers money for <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſuppoſing that Order very prejudiciall to the affairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and contrary to an Act of Parliament made this preſent Seſſion; Do in the firſt place Declare, That theſe directions given by His Majeſty for the retracting of this Order, is an high breach of priviledge of Parliament; And they cannot, without a deep ſenſe of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, call to minde how Popiſh and Prelaticall Counſells did ſo far prevail with his Majeſty, that two Armies were brought within the bowels of this Kingdom, and two Proteſtant Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ready to welter in each others blood; that when both thoſe Armies had been a long time defrayed at the charge of the poor Commons of <hi>England,</hi> and at length, by Gods bleſſing upon the endeavours of the Parliament, quietly disbanded, the ſame wicked Counſels (prevented of that deſigne) did ſoon after raiſe this bloody and barbarous Rebellion in <hi>Ireland:</hi> The ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing whereof (for the better colour) was recommended to the care of the Parliament; who, out of a fellow-feeling of the unſpeakable miſeries of their Proteſtant brethren there (not ſuſpecting this horrid Plot, now too apparent) did cheerfully undertake that great work, and do really intend and endeavour to ſettle the Proteſtant Religion, and a permanent Peace in that Realm, to the glory of God, and the great honour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of His Majeſty, and ſecurity of His three Kingdoms: But how they have been diſcouraged, retarded, and diverted in and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:132705:14"/> from this pious and glorious Work, by thoſe Trayterous coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells about His Majeſty, will appear by many particulars, ſome whereof they ſhall, upon this juſt occaſion, call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
            <p>That when the Lords and Commons had upon the firſt breaking out of the Rebellion, immediately provided and ſent over twenty thouſand pounds, and engaged themſelves and the whole Kingdom for the reducing of the Rebels; Yet His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, after His return from <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> was not either pleaſed by Word or Meſſage to take notice of it, untill after ſome in the Houſe of Commons had truely obſerved how for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thoſe miſchievous Counſellors were to incite His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty againſt His Proteſtant Subjects of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and how ſlow to recent the proceeding of His Papiſt Traytors in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That although the Rebells had moſt impudently ſtiled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>The Queens Army,</hi> and profeſt that the cauſe of their riſing was, To maintain the Kings Prerogative, and the Queens Religion, againſt the Puritan Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> And that thereupon both Houſes of Parliament did humbly and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adviſe His Majeſty to wipe away this dangerous ſcandall, by proclaiming them Rebels and Traytors to His Majeſty, and the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> which then would have mated and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Conſpirators in the beginning, and have encouraged both the Parliament here, and good people there, the more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly to have oppoſed their proceedings: Yet ſuch was the power of thoſe Counſells, that no Proclamation was ſet forth to that purpoſe, till almoſt three months after the breaking out of this Rebellion, and then Command given, That but 40 ſhould be Printed, nor they publiſhed, till further directions ſhould be given by His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>That after both Houſes of Parliament had found out a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable way to reduce the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of private men, without any charge to the Subject in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and which they are very confident would have brought in a Million of money (had His Majeſty continued in or neer <hi>London</hi>) thoſe malicious whiſperers, that durſt not hinder the paſſing of the Bill, which was ſo ſpecious in it ſelf, and ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally approved: Yet have by practiſe, by drawing His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:132705:15"/> from His Parliament, by keeping Him at this diſtance, and adviſing him to make War upon His People, ſo intimidated and diſcouraged the Adventurers, and others that would have adventured, that they have rendred that good Bill in a manner ineffectuall.</p>
            <p>That the Parliament and Adventurers had long ſince deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed five thouſand Foot, and five hundred Horſe for the relief of <hi>Munſter,</hi> to be ſent as a Brigade, under the command of the Lord <hi>Wharton;</hi> had made choice of, and liſted all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, and prepared Money, Arms, and other Proviſion for that Expedition, and all to be at the charge of the Adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: And when nothing was wanting, but a Commiſſion to the Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi> to enable him for that ſervice, ſuch was the power of thoſe Counſels, that no Commiſſion could be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from His Majeſty; by reaſon whereof, <hi>Lymbrick</hi> was wholly loſt, and the Province of <hi>Munſter</hi> is now in very great diſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>That when divers pious and well-affected perſons had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared twelve Ships, and ſix Pinnaces, with a thouſand or more Land-forces, at their own charge, by way of Adventure for the ſervice of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and deſired nothing but a Commiſſion from His Majeſty to enable them thereunto; that Commiſſion, after twice ſending to <hi>York</hi> for the ſame, and the Ships lying ready to ſet Sail for three weeks together, at the charge of neer three hundred pound a day, was likewiſe denied; and thoſe Adventurers (rather then to loſe their Expedition) were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to go by vertue of an Ordinance of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>That although the Lords Juſtices of <hi>Ireland</hi> have three moneths ſince earneſtly deſired to have two Pieces of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery ſent over, as very neceſſary for that ſervice, yet ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are given to the Officers of the Tower, That none of His Majeſties Ordnance muſt be ſent to ſave his Majeſties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>That although whilſt the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> ſtayed here in the Service of the Parliament, and in providing for his long-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Voyage into <hi>Ireland,</hi> a Meſſage was ſent to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament from His Majeſty to haſten him away, and Letters
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:132705:15"/> were written to the ſaid Earl from His Majeſty, that he ſhould make no ſtay at <hi>York</hi> for his diſpatch, but that his Inſtructions ſhould be ready for him againſt he came: And although it is notoriouſly known, That the Affairs of <hi>Ireland</hi> do exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſuffer by wanting the perſonall aſſiſtance of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief, to give both life and motion to the Army there; yet the ſaid Earl hath been ſtayed with His Majeſty in the North a month and more, and as yet can get no diſpatch.</p>
            <p>That notwithſtanding the bleeding condition of <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet divers Commanders and Officers in pay, and in actuall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment there againſt the Rebels, have been called away from that important Service, by the expreſſe Command of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as <hi>Charles Floyd,</hi> Engineer and Quarter-maſter Generall of the Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and divers others.</p>
            <p>That Captain <hi>Green,</hi> Comptroller of the Artillery, a man in pay, and principally employed and truſted here by the Lord-Lievtenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the providing and odering the Train of Artillery which was to be ſent to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and who had received great Sums of money for that purpoſe, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded from that employment and truſt, to ſerve His Majeſty in this moſt unnaturall War againſt His loyall and beſt-affected people.</p>
            <p>That the Parliament having made great proviſion of clothes for the poor Souldiers in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for their preſent ſuccour, and ſending ſix hundred ſuits, part thereof towards <hi>Cheſter</hi> the laſt week; the man that undertook the carriage of them, one <hi>William Whitaker</hi> by name, was aſſaulted by His Majeſties Cavaliers, then lying about <hi>Coventry,</hi> who took away theſe ſix hundred ſuits of clothes, and the Waggon and horſes of the poor man, although they were told that the ſix hundred ſuits of clothes were for the Souldiers in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the poor Carryer was five times with the Earl of <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampton,</hi> to beg a releaſe of his Waggon.</p>
            <p>That three hundred ſuits of clothes, with a Chirurgions Cheſt of Medicaments, being likewiſe ſent for <hi>Ireland</hi> by one <hi>Richard Owefield,</hi> who was employed by the Parliament to carry them to <hi>Cheſter,</hi> a Troop of His Majeſties Cavaliers, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der command of one Captain <hi>Middleton,</hi> met with them upon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:132705:16"/> the Road, and took away the clothes, and Chirurgeons Cheſt, together with the poor Carryers horſes and Waggon, for His Majeſties pretended ſervice here.</p>
            <p>That a great number of Draught-horſes prepared by the Parliament for the Artillery and Baggage of the Iriſh Army, were ſent to <hi>Cheſter</hi> for that purpoſe; and being there, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending a Paſſage, are now required by His Majeſty, for His ſaid preſent ſervice in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That His Majeſties Forces are ſo Quartered in and about the common Roads to <hi>Ireland,</hi> that neither Money, Clothes, Victualls, or other Proviſion can paſſe thither by Land with any ſafety.</p>
            <p>That Captain <hi>Kettleby</hi> the Admirall, and Sir <hi>Henry Strad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> the Vice-Admirall of the Ships which were directed to lie upon the Coaſt of <hi>Ireland</hi> to annoy the Rebells, and to prevent the bringing to them Ammunition and relief from forraign Parts, are both called away from that employment by His Majeſties Command; and by reaſon of their departure from the Coaſt of <hi>Munſter,</hi> to which they were deſigned, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells there have received Powder, Ammunition, and other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief from forraign parts; by which, and many other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, too long to relate, it may ſeem as if thoſe barbarous Iriſh Rebells are kept on foot and countenanced there, of deſigne to aſſiſt the Northern Cavaliers, and according to the Earl of <hi>Strafords</hi> unheard of advice, to have an Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> with which His Majeſty may reduce this Kingdom, eſpecially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thoſe confident Rebells have preſumed, very lately, to ſend a Petition to His Majeſty, intituling themſelves His Majeſties Catholike Subjects of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and complaining of the Puritane Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and deſiring, That ſince His Majeſty comes not thither, according to their expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they may come into <hi>England</hi> to His Majeſty; Which Petition, we may juſtly fear, is but a Prologue to that Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie they have deſigned to act here, in caſe their coming over be not prevented by the care and vigilancy of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and good people of <hi>England.</hi> But leſt the Houſe of Commons might ſeem to excuſe the making of this Order by a way of Recrimination, They, for ſatisfaction to the world, do
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:132705:16"/> proteſt before Almighty God (the ſearcher of all hearts) That they have as great compaſſion and ſorrow for the preſent ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of their diſtreſſed brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as if themſelves were in their caſe (into which they are confident thoſe horrid Traitours, thoſe monſters of men about His Majeſtie do labour to bring this Kingdom) That they have, and ſhall ever really endeavour by all means poſſible (with a due regard to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſtate of this Kingdom) to ſupply and ſupport them in this their great affliction, notwithſtanding the malice and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of all oppoſers.</p>
            <p>That the Houſe of Commons lively apprehending the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger of this Kingdom, and finding that whileſt they were active here to ſubdue the Rebels of <hi>Ireland,</hi> there were Papiſts, Traytors and Delinquents more active in the North, to conquer and deſtroy the Parliament and good people of <hi>England,</hi> Thought it neceſſary to provide for the ſafety of both, by preparing a competent Army for the defence of King and Kingdom. And although multitudes of well-affected perſons had cheerfully brought in great ſtore of Plate for that purpoſe, yet in regard the Plate could not be coyned with ſuch expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as the Importance of the Service did require, and well knowing that One hundred thouſand pounds might for a ſhort time be borrowed out of the Adventurers Money for <hi>Ireland,</hi> without any prejudice to the Affairs of that Kingdom, whoſe ſubſiſtence depends upon the well-fare of this, and reſolving to make a reall and ſpeedy re-payment of what Money ſhould be ſo borrowed, did make this Order; which, that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to all the world to be neither miſchievous, illegall, nor unjuſt (as His Majeſtie by the inſtigation of thoſe Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant whiſperers is pleaſed to tearm it) the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons thought fit to recite it, in <hi>haec verba;</hi> and in ſtead of retracting the Order, to re-pay the Money with all poſſible ſpeed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:132705:17"/>
            <opener>
               <date>The 30 of July, 1642.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>IT is this day Ordered by the Commons Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That the Treaſurers appointed to receive the Monies come in upon the Subſcriptions for</hi> Ireland, <hi>do forthwith furniſh by way of Loan, unto the Committee of the Lords and Commons, for the defence of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the ſum of One hundred thouſand pounds, for the ſupply of the publike neceſsitie, for the defence of the King, Parliament, and Kingdom, upon the publike Faith, to be re-paid duely and carefully within ſo ſhort a time, that it ſhall not be diverted from the purpoſe for, which it was intended, or any way fruſtrate the Acts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made in the behalf of that Adventure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY which Order, and that which hath been here truely ſet down, it will eaſily appear to all the indifferent people of His Majeſties three Kingdoms, whether the King and His Cavaliers, or the King and His Parliament do moſt affect and endeavour the ſetling of true Religion, and a firm and conſtant Peace within that bleeding and diſtreſſed Kingdom.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="affidavit">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:132705:17"/>
            <head>The examination of Collonell <hi>Audley Mervin</hi> given in the fifth day of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1643. unto a ſelect Committee of the Houſe of Commons, and atteſted under his hand.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Examinate ſaith that about the 27 of <hi>October 1641. Rory Maguire,</hi> brother to the Lord <hi>Maguire,</hi> came unto Caſtle <hi>Trelick,</hi> in the County of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> being this Examinates then houſe, who amongſt other diſcourſe told this Examinate, that it was reſolved amongſt themſelves, to imploy him into <hi>England,</hi> to repreſent unto his Majeſtie, upon what grounds they had taken up Armes, and what deſires being granted, they would lay them downe: the reaſons <hi>Rory Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guire</hi> acquainted this examinate withall for the preſent were, that the Parliament in <hi>England</hi> was fully bent to the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Catholique Religion, as was apparent in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of ſome of their prieſts, and <hi>that they invaded the Kings prerogative in which their greateſt ſecurity repoſed.</hi> To the firſt, I anſwered him, the power of the Parliament in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> extended only to that Kingdome, their ſtatutes obliged not us untill confirmed it being found agreable to the conſtitution, of this Kingdome, by our owne Parliament. As to the ſecond,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:132705:18"/> we were no competent Iudges of the Parliaments procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and it were ſeaſonable enough to vindicate the Kings prerogative, when his Majeſtie had declared it wounded, and had commanded his aſſiſtance, and deſired further to know, in what high poynt, thoſe poore proteſtant ſoules al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready murthered, had offended his Majeſties prerogative. Hee replied, that when he came next with the heads of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance unto mee, hee would ſatiſfie mee in every ſcruple. Upon his departure, this examinate called him aſide, adviſing him (in reſpect the ſaid <hi>Rory Maguire</hi> had married his ſiſter, and by her got 900 pounds <hi>per annum</hi> inheritance, that hee would deſiſt from further proſecuting ſo barbarous, and treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable a deſigne, and that it were feizable to procure his pardon, if he would beſtow his endeavours in appeaſing this Rebellion; but howſoever hee aſſuming at the preſent the power to ſend Proclamations into the Countrey) except he would repreſſe the fury of the fire, and ſword, and ſuch other acts of hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, by publique notice given to the Countrey, that I durſt not addreſſe my ſelf unto his Majeſtie, ſince the ſubject, I feared, would receive but a cold welcome at the beſt, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when it ſhould be dyed in ſo much innocent bloud: which he accordingly did, and this examinate gave notice to the Proteſtants about him, to diſpoſe of themſelves towards <hi>Derrey</hi> and that hee would adventure himſelf the laſt man, and ſo by the bleſſing of God many were ſaved, and this exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, his wife, two ſiſters, and his children eſcaped in the night, ſaving nothing but their lives: ſuch as remayned being deluded by the Rebells promiſes, and wedded to their owne habitations were maſſacred. This examinate further ſaith, that amongſt other dehortatorie reaſons uſed to <hi>Rory Maguire</hi> hee alleadged, that admit the Papiſts could for the preſent roote the Proteſtants out, yet they, nor their poſterity, could never enjoy a peaceable ſetlement, whilſt <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſurvived. To this hee replyed, that the Catholique Princes would aſſiſt them <hi>viz. France,</hi> &amp; <hi>Spaine.</hi> I anſwered if it were ſo, they would be well paid for their paynes, and that it were
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:132705:18"/> better to reſt with their peaceable government in their hand, then to dreame after a fained, and uncertaine priviledge in the buſh; and that I could aſſure him, thoſe Princes were in a condition of borrowing ſupplies, not lending any. This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminate remembers well his Reply, <hi>viz.</hi> Come, come brother, deceive not your ſelf, in being too wiſe, all <hi>Ireland</hi> is at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in our hands, I will ſhew you all the places of ſtrength to what perſons their ſupriſall was aſſigned, <hi>this great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking was never the Act of one or two giddy fellowes, wee have our party in</hi> England, <hi>wee have our party in</hi> Scotland, <hi>that ſhall keepe them buſie for ſending you any ayd,</hi> I aſſure you tis well if they can ſave themſelves, and before you can get thither, you will finde them, (if they be not already) <hi>as deepe in bloud as our ſelves.</hi> He further added, if you will reſolve to goe, I will come within three or foure dayes, and then you ſhall know all; if you will not, I will convoy you, and yours ſafe to the next port, and ſee you imbarqued, Provided you ſweare, never to come over to fight againſt us. But I fearing this was to ſound me, and that ſo many lives depended upon my demeaſner; I replyed, bring your heads, the ſooner the better; but unwilling to truſt to any further curteſies eſcaped before his returne; <hi>He told me this plot had beene of ancient date, and many times diſcontinued, but it had beene lively re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, and proſecuted from Candlemas last paſt, before the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, both in</hi> England, <hi>and</hi> Scotland. <hi>All which I have heard from many more of very conſiderable quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Audley Mervin.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="affidavit">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:132705:19"/>
            <head>
               <hi>William Stewart</hi> Eſquire, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Iuly</hi> 8. 1643. by a ſelect Committee of the Houſe of Commons, ſaith,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat he being a Priſoner ſix Moneths among the Rebels in <hi>Vlſter,</hi> from the middeſt of <hi>November</hi> 1641. he heard <hi>Tyrlagh ô Neale,</hi> and <hi>Roger ô More,</hi> and the principall men in <hi>Vlſter</hi> ſay, that Religion, the lands eſcheated, and the <hi>Kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> were the prime cauſes of their riſing in Armes; that they knew well <hi>the beſt of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>would ſide with them;</hi> that <hi>they had good warrant in black and white for what they did:</hi> that when he objected, the power of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> would bee brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they replyed that there was little feare of that; <hi>For the troubles of</hi> England <hi>were but then in beginning, and would not end in haſt;</hi> That he ſhould ſee the King ere long in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>VVilliam Stewart.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="affidavit">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:132705:19"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Henry Stewart</hi> Gentleman Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined 8 <hi>Iuly</hi> 1643. before a ſelect Committee of the Houſe of Commons ſaith,</head>
            <p>THat at <hi>Michaelmas</hi> 1642. at the ſurrender up of the Caſtle of <hi>Dungannon</hi> to the Rebells, Sir <hi>Philemon ô Neale</hi> was deſirous to know of this Examinate what forces General <hi>Leſley</hi> had with him, and what authority hee had, whether from King or Parliament, or both, he told Sir <hi>Philemon</hi> from both, which he would not beleeve, but ſaid, <hi>That ere long the troubles of</hi> England <hi>would call</hi> Leſley <hi>away to aſsiſt them,</hi> and that he did not beleeve he had the Kings Commiſſion, but hee hoped ere long to kiſſe the Kings hand, before thoſe that were his greateſt enemies.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Stewart.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:132705:20"/>
            <head>10 <hi>November</hi> 1641. A Copie of a Letter directed to the Lord <hi>Viceco. Coſtiloe,</hi> from the Rebells of the Countie of <hi>Longford</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which he preſented to the State in their behalfe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Our very good Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur alliance unto your Lordſhips Anceſtors and your ſelfe, and the tryall of your and their performance of truſt unto their friends in their greateſt adverſitie encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth us, and engageth your honour to our fruition of your future favours; the fixion of our confidence in you before any other of the Peeres, and Privie Counſellers of the Kingdome doubleth this obligation. Your Lordſhip may be therefore pleaſed to acquaint the Lords, Juſtices, and Councell, (to bee imparted unto his Sacred Majeſtie) with our grievances, and the cauſes thereof, the redreſſe which we moſt humbly pray, and the manner of it; Firſt, the Papiſts in neighbouring Countries are ſeverely puniſhed, and their miſerie might ſerve for Beacons unto us, to looke unto our owne, when our neighbours houſes are afire, and wee and other Papiſts are, and ever will be as loyall ſubjects, as any in the King his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions: for manifeſtation whereof, we ſend herein encloſed an oath ſolemnly taken by us, which as it received indeleble impreſſion in our hearts ſhall be ſigned with our hands, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:132705:20"/> ſealed with our blood. Secondly, there is an incapacitie in the Papiſts of honour, Offices, and the immunities of true ſubjects, the royall markes of diſtributive Juſtice, and a disfavour in the commutative, which raiſed ſtrangers and forrainers, whoſe valour and vertue was inviſible, when the old families of the Engliſh, and the major part of us, the meere Iriſh, did ſwim in blood to ſerve the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> and when Offices ſhould call for men of worth, men without worth, or merit obtained them. Thirdly, the Statute of 2 <hi>Eliz.</hi> of force in this Kingdome againſt us and others of our Religion, doth not a little diſanimate us and the reſt. Fourthly, the avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of grants of our Lands and liberties by quirkes and quiddities of law, without reflecting upon the King his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and reall intention for confirming our eſtates, his broad Seale being the pawne betweene his Majeſtie and his people. Fifthly, the reſtraint of purchaſe in the meere Iriſh of lands in the eſcheated Counties, and the taint and blemiſh of them and their poſterities, doth more diſcontent them then that Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion rule, for they are brought to that exigent of povertie in theſe late times, that they muſt be ſellers, and not buyers of lands. And we conceive, and humbly offer to your Lordſhips conſideration (<hi>Principiis obſta</hi>) that in the beginning of this Commotion, your Lordſhip as it is hereditarie for you, will be a Phyſitian to cure this diſeaſe in us, and by our exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples it will doubtleſſe beget the like auſpicious ſucceſſe in all other parts of the Kingdome, for we are of opinion it is one ſickneſſe, and one <hi>Pharmack</hi> will ſuffice; <hi>ſublata cauſa tollitur effectus.</hi> And it will be recorded, that you will doe ſervice unto God, King and Countrie, and for ſalving every the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned ſoares, your Lordſhip to <hi>bee an humble ſuiter in our behalfe, and of the rest of the Papiſts, that out of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his Majesties Clemencie, there may be an Act of obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, and generall pardon without reſtitution, or accompt of goods taken in the time of this Commotion, a libertie of our Religion, a repeale of all Statutes formerly made to the contrary, and not by Proclamation, but Parliamentary way;</hi> A Charter of free De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizen
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:132705:21"/> in ample manner for the meere Iriſh, which in all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceeding ages will prove an union in all his Majeſties Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in ſtead of diviſion, a comfort for deſolations, and a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in perpetuitie for an imminent calamitie; and this being granted, there will be all things, <hi>quae ſunt Caeſaris Caeſari,</hi> and <hi>quae ſunt Dei Deo.</hi> And as it was by the Poet written, though he be prophane in other matters, yet in this Propheticall, <hi>Diviſum Imperium cum love Caeſar habet.</hi> All which for this preſent we leave to your Honourable care; And we will, as ever we did, and doe, remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <date>Decimo Novembr. 1641.</date>
               <signed>Your very humble and aſſured ever to be commanded,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hugh mas Gillernow Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iames Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bryan Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Readagh Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edmund mac Cahell Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Farrall in Carbuy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Garret Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Liſagh mac Conell Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Brian mac William Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn mac Edmond Farral.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Farral.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roger mac Bryne Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Barnaby Farrall</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iames mac Teig Farr.</hi> his marke</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Morgan mac Carbry Farral.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Donagh mac Carbry Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard mac Conel Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>VVilliam mac Iames Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iames Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Taghna mac Rory Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cormack mac Rory Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Conock mac Bryne Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Readagh mac Liſagh Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Connor Oge mac Conor Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edmond mac Connor Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cahell mac Bryne Farrall.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:132705:21"/>
            <head>To the Honourable <hi>William Lenthall</hi> Eſquire, Speaker of the Houſe of Commons pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent theſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>VVorthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Lines are ſent to give you this further accompt of our proceedings ſince my laſt from <hi>Stafford</hi> upon Thurſday <hi>May</hi> 30. that God who delivered the Town of <hi>Namptwich</hi> from three attempts of our Enemies of <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church,</hi> did notwithſtanding upon the firſt attempt made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Whitchurch,</hi> deliverd the ſame into our hands, and foure peeces of Ordnance, ſome Powder, Armes, Horſes, and much Treaſure which was taken, but concealed by ſome of the common Souldiers and others; All their Carriages, cloaths, proviſions, and ſome horſes taken; Two of their Captaines and other perſons of worth ſlaine, and one Captaine, and ſome other perſons of qualitie taken Priſoners; The Lord was pleaſed much to appeare in this dayes ſucceſſe; and to aſſiſt our men with invincible and indefatigable courage, ſo farre as to enable them to make their entrance upon the mouth of their Cannon; There were twentie of theirs ſlaine out right, and not above two or three of ours, Colonell <hi>VVinne,</hi> Colonell <hi>Crow,</hi> Serjeant Major Generall <hi>VVoodhouſe,</hi> and the moſt of their prime Commanders eſcaped; Their Cannonier was kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a ſhot made by our Cannoniere: we were not poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:132705:22"/> of one Peece of Cannon at our entrance into this Countie, yet now God hath pleaſed plentifully to furniſh us with ſix peeces at <hi>Namptwich,</hi> and two at <hi>Stafford,</hi> ſo as wee now want Cannoniors to order and manage the ſame. ☞ <hi>VVith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a few dayes after this victory there landed in two Barkes many Iriſh Rebels in</hi> Worrall <hi>in Cheſhire, ſome whereof acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in the Preſence of divers ſufficient men, who affirmed the ſame unto me, that they had waſhed their hands in the blood of divers Engliſh and Scots in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and now hoped to waſh their hands in the blood of Engliſh men in</hi> England; <hi>Which Rebels being brought into</hi> Cheſter, <hi>were accuſed by ſeverall of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons who came to</hi> Cheſter <hi>for refuge, to be the perſons who cut their husbands throats; others that they ripped up their childrens bowels. The Countrey wherein they firſt arrived, did apprehend ſo much diſtaſte, that they did all riſe with their beſt weapons, and apprehended divers of the Iriſh Rebles; but being unarmed, not having above ſeven or 8 Muſqueteers, they could not make good their Priſoners, who were reſcued out of their hands by a troope of horſe, which came from the Commiſſioners of Array, who alſo ſeized about 28 of our honeſt Countrey-men priſoners. Theſe Iriſh acknowledge they came from Strongforth, and that there are 1200. ſome ſpeake of 10000 more to follow after.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir, </salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant,</hi> Will. Brereton.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Liverpoole</hi> 
                  <date>Iune 1643.</date>
               </dateline>

               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:132705:22"/>

               <dateline>Read in the Houſe of Commons <date>Ianuary 14.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>We have placed a Garriſon in this Towne, which (I hope) may be of great Advantage, being the onely Haven Town in theſe parts of the Kingdome.</p>
            </postscript>
            <postscript>
               <p>Poſt.</p>
               <p>SInce I writ the lines above, two of our Long Boats which were manned and ſent out are returned, and have brought in the Boats which carried the Rebels, and have taken three or foure of the Rebells, who confeſſe they came from <hi>Strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and that they were ſent by one Maſter <hi>Savage:</hi> they have alſo ſeized ſome Barques laden with Wine, part where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of belonges to thoſe who are well affected to you, and have ſuffered in your cauſe; But the greateſt part to thoſe who are engaged againſt you, which is reſerved here to be diſpoſed of as you ſhall pleaſe to order and direct.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter_of_marque">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:132705:23"/>
            <head>A letter of Mart</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>(<hi>Warwicke,</hi> Lord <hi>Mohun,</hi> Baron of <hi>Okehampton,</hi> Sir) <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> knight of the <hi>Bath; Sir</hi> Iohn Barkeley, knight; and <hi>William Aſhbourneham</hi> Eſquire, or any two of them Commiſſioners authorized under the great ſeal of <hi>England,</hi> in the abſence of William Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, of <hi>Hertford;</hi> to command all his Majeſties forces in the <hi>Weſt.</hi>
               </signed> To <hi>George Chappell</hi> of <hi>Topeſham</hi> Merchant.</opener>
            <p>VVEE doe hereby nominate, authorice, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt, you <hi>George Chappell</hi> to bee Captaine and chiefe commander of a ſhip called the Hope of <hi>Topeſham,</hi> requiring you with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and expedition, to endeavour the furniſhing and compleating of her with men, victuall, and ammunition, as alſo with tackell, and furniture, fit for a voyage to ſea, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding all inferiour officers, ſouldiers, mariners, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, under your command in the ſaid ſhip, and veſſell to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey you as their Captaine, according to this Commiſſion, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorizing you to ſet to ſea at any time, and as often as you in your diſcretion ſhall thinke fit, for the ſpace of ſix moneths next enſuing. And during the ſaid time to apprehend ſeiſe, and take for his Majeſties ſervice all ſuch Shipps, barques, and veſſells, as doe belong to the Citties, towns, and ports of <hi>London, Exeter, Hull, Portmouth, Dartmouth, Barneſtable, Bideford,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:132705:23"/> and <hi>Plimmouth,</hi> or to any of them, or to any other Cities, Townes, or Ports of this Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> now in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt his Majeſtie, or to the inhabitants of the ſame or any of them: And the ſame to carry or bring into any of his Majeſties Ports, or harbours, within the Countie of <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall.</hi> That the ſaid ſhipp, or goods ſo taken by you, together with the Merchants, Officers, maſters and Seamen may be proceeded againſt according to the lawes of this Land; giving you alſo full power and authority in caſe of reſiſtance to kill, and ſlay all ſuch as ſhall reſiſt you in the execution of this your commiſſion. And you are likewiſe to obſerve, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch orders, and directions, as from time to time you ſhall receive from us.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under our hands, and ſeales at <hi>Honyton</hi> 
                  <date>the firſt day of <hi>Iune Anno Domini</hi> 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Warwick Mohum,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Berkeley.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:132705:24"/>
            <head>By the Supream Councell of the confederate Catholiques of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO all men, to whom this preſent ſhall come we the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Councell, of the confederate Catholiques of this Realme ſend greeting; Know yee that wee having taken into our ſerious conſideration the great and neceſſarie uſe, wee have of ſhips of warre, for the defence of the coaſts of this Realme, and advancement, and furtherance of commerce with forraign Nations, and for oppoſing of his Majeſties Enemies, who daily hinder and annoy <hi>his Majeſties good Subjects of this Kingdome by Sea,</hi> and ſtop all the Free trade in this Realme and abroad. Have therefore conſtituted, and appointed, and doe hereby ordaine conſtitute, and appoint Our wellbeloved Friend Captaine <hi>Francis Oliver,</hi> native of Flanders having received good teſtimony of his ſufficiency, and integritiy to be Captain of the ſhip called Saint <hi>Michaell the Archangell</hi> of burden an hundred and twentie Laſts or Tuns, or thereabouts Hereby giving and granting, unto the ſaid, Captaine full and abſolute power, Commiſſion and, authority to furniſh the ſaid ſhip, with all neceſſaries fit for ſea, and warre, and with the ſame to croſſe the ſeas, and take hinder and prejudice all ſuch as he ſhall find or meet <hi>of his Majeſtics enemies, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the generall Catholique cauſe now in hand in this Kingdome,</hi> their ſhips and goods whatſoever, either by ſea or Land, by what means ſoever, and the ſaid ſhipping or Goods to ſet to ſale, and diſpoſe of as lawfull prizes, and open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies goods, ſaving <hi>unto his Majcſtie and his lawfull officers,</hi> and to all other perſon or perſons bodies politique and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, all rights, requiſites, and duties due or uſually an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered out of all prizes. And we hereby command all officers of all Ports, and Harbours, and Havens, within our Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, throughout this Realme to admit the ſaid Captaine <hi>Francis Oliver,</hi> and his Companies, ſhips and goods from time to time to paſſe, and repaſſe, come and goe without moleſtation or
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:132705:24"/> trouble; and that all Commanders of forts, and all other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of his Majeſties loving ſubjects to be aiding and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting unto him in execution, and furtherance of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes whatſoever and as often as occaſion ſhall require.</p>
            <p>And laſtly we pray all forraigne Princes States, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates to defend, protect, aſſiſt, and favour the ſaid Captain his ſhips and goods, when and as often as he ſhall come into their reſpective coaſts and harbours.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>This our Commiſſion to continue during our pleaſure. Given at <hi>Kilkennie</hi> 
                  <date>the laſt of <hi>December.</hi> 1642.</date>
               </dateline> Was ſigned,
<signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mountgarret, Hugo Ardmachanus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gormanſton. Ioannes Epiſcop: Clonfertenſis,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N. Plunket, Patr. Darcy,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iames Cuſack Geffr. Browne.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <signed>Sealed At a Labell in parchment with a ſeale of yellow wax bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the marke of a long croſſe, on the right ſide whereof a Crown; and a harpe on the left, with a dove above, and a flaming heart below the croſſe, and round about this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription. <hi>Pro Deo, pro Rege &amp; patria Hibernia unanimis.</hi>
               </signed>
               <signed>And Endorſed thus, <hi>Memorandum</hi> this Patent is inrolled in the Admiraltie Court of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that the whithin Captaine hath ſworne and given ſecurity of his fidelitie according to the uſuall forme, </signed>
               <date>Witnes my hand the 5 <hi>March</hi> 1642.</date>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Iames Cuſack</hi> Judge Admiralty.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="affidavit">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:132705:25"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>Iohn Davice</hi> Eſquire, taken before a ſelect Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of the Houſe of Commons 13. <hi>Iuly</hi> 1643.</head>
            <p>SAith, that two Ships, the one called the <hi>Michael</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sydrach Pope</hi> being ſent therein for <hi>France</hi> with 648 Hydes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade corne for the reliefe of the Proteſtant Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie in <hi>Vlſter,</hi> was by foule weather in <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> laſt forced into <hi>Falmouth,</hi> and there ſeiſed on by Sir <hi>Nich. Slaney,</hi> and manned with ſome Muſquettiers of his ſent unto Saint <hi>Mallo</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> where the Hides were ſold, and the proceed returned unto him in the ſaid Ship in powder, match, Ammunition &amp;c. And further ſaith, that about the 20 of <hi>April</hi> laſt one <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam King</hi> of <hi>Dover</hi> his Ship being laden with 90 tunnes of Wine and ſalt from <hi>France,</hi> and bound for <hi>Carrickfergus</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> upon the examinaets accompt, was upon the Coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> taken by one <hi>Rich. Iones,</hi> Captaine of a ſhip ſet out from <hi>Falmouth</hi> with his Majeſties Warrant, and the ſhip and goods were ſold by him at <hi>Brest</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IOHN DAVICE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="affidavit">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:132705:25"/>
            <head>Great-Yarmouth. <hi>The Examination of</hi> Chriſtopher Haſſall <hi>of</hi> Waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford <hi>in</hi> Ireland <hi>Sayler, taken this 12 of July, 1643. as followeth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHo ſaith, that he was preſt by the Major of <hi>Waſhford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Nicholas Hayes,</hi> about ten daies ſince, into a Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirke Frigot called the Patricke, <hi>to ſerve the King of England at Sea, in taking and pillaging ſuch Ships and Veſſels as were not for the King;</hi> of which Frigot one <hi>George Prun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas</hi> a Dunkirker was chiefe Commander and Captaine, and <hi>Walter Hayes</hi> an Iriſh-man was Captaine under him, and had about an hundred men in the Ship, and eleven pieces of Ordinance, and came out to the Sea the fourth of this inſtant June, and tooke and pillaged ſince they came out: Firſt, an Apſome Barke, which after ſhe was pillaged they ſunke in the Sea, having taken out of her eleven packs of Cloth; and after that tooke a Fiſherboat of <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> upon Saturday laſt, and tooke out of her an hundred North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea Cod-fiſh, and fourteene peeces of eight, and a double Piſtoll, and pillaged the Veſſell of all they could get, and of the mens Cloathes; and then put in the Apſome men taken out of the ſunke ſhip, and ſo let them goe. And after that tooke a Scottiſh Barke, and a <hi>Dover</hi> barke, and a Pram or Hute, and a Catch; and tooke ſeven men out of the Pram, and two men out of the Scot, beſides the Maſter, and three men out of the Catch, and carried them away in the Frigot, and put other men of their owne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board; And afterward two of theſe Veſſels ſo taken being reſcued by Captaine <hi>Wilde,</hi> Commander of the ſhip, the Cygnet, in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for King and Parliament, were brought into <hi>Yarmouth</hi> rode this day, with this examinate being in one of them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The marke of Chriſtopher Haſſall is ſubſcribed.</signed>
               <signed>Capt. per Giles Call Iohn Symond <hi>Bayliffs.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="affidavit">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:132705:26"/>
            <head>Great-Yarmouth. The Examination of <hi>Marke Roch</hi> of <hi>Waſhford</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> Mariner, taken this twelfth day of June, 1643.</head>
            <p>THis examinate ſaith, that he is one of the Quarter-maſters of the Dunkirke Frigot, and was ſhipped by the Major of <hi>Waſhford</hi> to ſerve in the ſaid Frigot under two Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, whereof the one was a Dunkirker called Capraine <hi>George Pruncas,</hi> the other an Iriſhman called Captaine <hi>Walter Hayes,</hi> who had Commiſſion to examine all they ſhould meet withall, <hi>whether they were for the King or Parliament; and if they were for the King to let them goe, and if for the Parlirment to take and pillage them;</hi> and did take firſt an Apſome man upon friday at night laſt, and pillaged the Ship, and tooke out of her divers packs of Cloth, being as he ſuppoſeth ſix or ſeven packs, and tooke the men alſo aboard and ſunke the Ship: and next day after tooke a <hi>Yarmouth</hi> Fiſher-boat at <hi>Ortford Neſſe:</hi> and tooke out of her certaine Fiſh, and pillaged Cloathes, and put the <hi>Apſome</hi> men aboard her, and ſo let them goe. And after that they tooke an Engliſh Hoy or Catch yeſterday morning, and what they did with her, he, this examinate knoweth not (it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his quarter;) and then tooke a Scottiſh Barke, and pillaged the men, and commited the Veſſell to <hi>Hugh Kelley</hi> another Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-maſter. And then tooke a <hi>Dover</hi> Ship laden with Coales, and pillaged her, which was after taken by Captaine <hi>Wilde,</hi> and is now comming into <hi>Yarmouth</hi>-rode. And alſo he ſaith that they took yeſterday a Forrain laden with deales, and tooke out the Maſter and ſeven of the Company, and the reſt got away with their veſſels and are gon to <hi>London.</hi> And yeſterday in the after noone this exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate being in the <hi>Dover</hi>-barke, which was committed to his charge, Captaine <hi>Wilde</hi> Commander of the Ship, the Cygnet, in ſervice for the King and Parliament, fell upon the ſaid Frigoe, and shot at her, and was in fight with her about two houres, but could
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:132705:26"/> not take her, becauſe she fled away, and was more ſwift in ſayle then he, but tooke this examinate with the <hi>Dover</hi>-barke, and ſent them into this roade of <hi>Yarmouth.</hi> And alſo he ſaith, that there are halfe a dozen more Ships at <hi>Waſhford,</hi> fitted and made ready to come forth upon the like ſervice that the ſaid Frigot came out for.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Marke Roch his name is ſubſcribed.</signed>
               <signed>Capt. per<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Giles Call</hi> Bayliffs.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Symond</hi> Bayliffs.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn Carter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Gower.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>For his Noble friend Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley,</hi> Knight, Governour of <hi>Scharborough,</hi> theſe:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe are ſhewing your honour, that my Lord of <hi>Aboyne</hi> was gone from <hi>Yorke</hi> before my here comming, therefore I will intreat your honour to have ſuch a care of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition appertaining to my Lord of <hi>Aboyne,</hi> as your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſhall have of my Lord of <hi>Antrim</hi> his Ammunition, till ſuch time as I either come my ſelfe, or write to your honour; For Mr. <hi>Jermyn</hi> hath deſired me to write theſe lines to your Honour, for I am commanded to goe for <hi>Scotland</hi> for that effect, to which time, I ſhall continue,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humble ſervant, Serjeant-major Roſſe.</signed>
               <dateline>Yorke, <date>May 8. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:132705:27"/>
            <head>For my Noble Lord the Earle of <hi>Antrim,</hi> at <hi>Yorke.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Noble Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MAtters are fallen out quite contrary to my expectation, ſo as I ſhould not adviſe you to make ſuch haſt of your journey as we reſolved. I have ſent this bearer of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, who is the man I did ſend to <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> who will particularly ſhew you how matters goe, and how great folly it were to looke for any aſſiſtance from <hi>Scotland.</hi> Good Sir <hi>Richard Grahame,</hi> and a number of roundheads in theſe parts, upon your ſervants remaining here, and your Lordſhips other ſervants com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming poſt, have ſpread a report that you and I, were upon a plot, to bring Forces from <hi>Ireland,</hi> to take in this Countrey; in ſo much as I have been forced to affirme the contrary with oathes, as I might juſtly doe. Thus much is given out by him, one <hi>Dalſton,</hi> and others as in acquittall to your Lady, for raiſing him out of the dunghill, which my Lord her husband did. He will be at <hi>Yorke</hi> within two or three daies, he will ſhift it off upon the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans of this Countrey, whereof he is the head: but upon my word your Lordſhip is little beholding to him. To my knowledge your Lordſhips ſervant will more particularly ſhew what paſſed; Nor ſhall any be more ready to doe you ſervice, then</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Carlile,</hi> 
                  <date>May 2. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humble ſervant, Nithiſdaill.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I did ſay that your Lordſhips Lady having ſome Hangings and other Furniture in <hi>Knock fergus</hi> was deſirous to have them brought away, but I had now adviſed you rather to let them alone for the preſent.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:132705:27"/>
            <head>For my Noble Lord, the Earle of <hi>Antrim,</hi> at <hi>York.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Noble Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have daily expected theſe dayes paſt to have writ, which you deſired, from the party you know, I doe look for it each hour. <hi>Hamilton,</hi> I doe fear, hath done bad offices to the King ſince his return. My Lord I am very confident <hi>Montros</hi> will not flinch from what he profeſſed at <hi>York.</hi> I thinke much, I have heard no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from my Lord <hi>Aboyne,</hi> but before I ſhall ſee you, I looke with confidence to give you a better account how matters are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſhall never leave off to give full teſtimony that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips faithfull ſervant, Nithiſdail.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>My Lord, blame not your ſervant who hath been ſo long here. I would not ſuffer him to part till I had ſome greater aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (from the Earle of <hi>Montros,</hi> and thereof who are for the K.) then as yet, and till my ſervants return I can give</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>For the Right Honourable, my Noble Lord, the Earle of <hi>Antrim</hi> at <hi>Yorke.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My noble Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT ſhould have been a blemiſh upon me, if I had not truly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you notice how matters go. I am not altogether deſperate of <hi>Montros;</hi> but ſay he were changed, I am in good hope you ſhall not lack well-affected Subjects in <hi>Scotland</hi> to proſecute that point we reſolved on. One thing I think ſtrange, that the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition granted to your Lordſhip and <hi>Aboyne</hi> ſhould be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. My Lord, without that, neither can the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> doe ſervice, nor can your friends in the Iſles and Hilands be uſefull for you. So doe your beſt to have it quickly ſent away, and be confident you ſhall have aſſiſtance, though it muſt take a longer time, of the which I ſhall give your Lordſhip notice. So let no
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:132705:28"/> alteration be thought upon, though a little it muſt be deferred. And be confident of the reſpects of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips faithfull ſervant, Nithiſdail.</signed>
               <dateline>Carlile <date>the 8. of May. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I entreat theſe may preſent my bounden ſervice to my Lady Dutcheſſe, your Lady. Till I get advertiſement from your Lordſhip, I ſhall have a Boat ready at your ſervice.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>For my Noble Lord, the Earle of <hi>Antrim</hi> at <hi>Yorke.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Gentleman can ſo well informe you of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars you expected from <hi>Scotland,</hi> as I muſt onely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your Lordſhip, I dare not conclude with him; therefore if it pleaſe you to expect a ſecond adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, it ſhall certainly bee ſent to you by the firſt occaſion. For I ſhould be ſorry, that what may ſo concerne your ſervice ſhould be ſubject to any ſcruple. And I aſſure your Lordſhip their future ſhall ratifie this opinion of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble ſervant Aboyne.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Burroughbridge</hi> in haſte <date>the 3. of May. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>For the Right Honourable, the Earle of <hi>Antrim,</hi> theſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing certainly informed by <hi>Nithiſdails</hi> ſervant, That there is<note place="margin">☞</note> a new Order ſince we parted for ſtopping of the Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I have taken occaſion to intreat your Lordship by this bearer, that I may know the particulars of it. I muſt confeſſe it ſurpriſeth me, that any diſtance ſhould alter ſo reaſonable a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. And certainly, I ſhall never deſerve to be made the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of fruſtrating the hopes of theſe parts, which ſhould have bin
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:132705:28"/> enabled by this ſupply. I am confident, there is ſcarce another mean to make our fidelitie <hi>uſeleſſe for her Majeſties ſervice.</hi> And if it pleaſe your Lordship to acquaint <hi>the Queene</hi> with theſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of my ingenuitie, you will thereby multiply your favours you have already conferred upon</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord, </salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt affectionate and obliged ſervant, Aboyne.</signed>
               <dateline>Carlile <date>the 8. of May. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the Earle of <hi>Antrim,</hi> theſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WIlliam</hi> Earle of <hi>Neweaſtle,</hi> Governour of the Towne and County of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and Generall of all His Majeſties Forces raiſed in the Northerne parts of this Kingdome for defence of the ſame.</p>
            <p>To all Colonels, Lieutenant-Colonels, Serjeant-Majors, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and all other his Majeſties loving Subjects of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as much as the Right Honourable, the Earle of <hi>Antrim</hi> is to travell to <hi>Dublyn</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and other parts of that Kingdom, theſe are therefore to deſire and require you, and every of you to whom this shall come to be ſeen, to permit and ſuffer him and his ſervants quietly and peaceably to paſſe and repaſſe into theſe parts, and backe againe without any moleſtation or interruption. And further, I doe hereby require all Poſt-maſters, Conſtables, and other Officers, to furnish the ſaid Earle and his ſervants with ſo many Poſt-horſes as they shall have neede of from place to place, and Stage to Stage for all the ſaid journey, he and they pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uſuall rates for the ſame. And hereof you or any of you may not faile at your perill: <hi>Given under my hand and ſeal the fourth day of May.</hi> 1643.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ſigned <hi>Will. Neweaſtle,</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:132705:29"/>
            <head>
               <hi>June</hi> 9. 1643. A Declaration of the Lords of His MAIESTIES Privie-Councell in SCOTLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lords of his Majeſties moſt honourable Privy-Councel, and the Commiſſioners for conſerving of the Peace, according to the great truſt repoſed on them by his Majeſtie and the Eſtates of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, whereof they are to make account to God and his Majeſtie the next enſuing Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, taking to their deepeſt and moſt ſerious conſideration the the beſt wayes of preſerving the peace of this Kingdom, That all his Majeſties good and dutifull Subjects may enjoy their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Liberties, and Laws, which God in a ſingular and wonderfull providence, in the time of his Majeſties raign hath vouchſafed them, and of the peace betwixt the two Kingdomes ſo unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly and happily eſtabliſhed in the late Treaty of peace, and in the Parliaments of both Kingdoms, Have faithfully endeavoured by all good means to reduce <hi>Ireland</hi> to his Majeſties obedience, which through the unnaturall, barbarous, and Antichriſtian cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of Papiſts, is from a peaceable Kingdome turned into a ſtage of unexampled and unexpreſſible miſeries, to be looked upon as an horrid and dangerous example by this Kingdom, and by their nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſupplications to his Majeſtie, and their Declarations to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> but eſpecially by their earneſt deſires for eſtablishing Unity of Religion, and Uniformity of Kirk-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for disbanding all Papiſts in Arms within their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and by the humble offer of their meditation to remove the unhappy differences, and quench the fire of a waſting Warre, begun betwixt his Majeſtie and his Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> wherein his Majeſties ſacred Perſon is expoſed to ſo great danger, and ſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:132705:29"/> many thouſands of his Subjects have already perished: But find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their great griefe the ſucceſſe no way anſwerable to their endeavours and expectation, and the trouble of the neighbouring Kingdoms, and the dangers of this Kingdome daily ariſing to a greater height, then they by their care, counſell, and diligence, were able to remeid or obviate, they did reſolve for this and other cauſes, which exerciſe and heavily preſſe the Kingdome at this time, to call a covention of the Eſtates, as the onely meane (his Majeſtie not thinking fit to hearken unto their motion of calling a Parliament) which might by common Counſell, conſent and reſolution, take the beſt courſe for repreſenting yet more ſenſibly theſe manifold evils and dangers and for overcomming by greater wiſdom the difficulties which were above their power.</p>
            <p>In the meane while (which they cannot but attribute to the mercifull and marvellous providence of God, and which is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation to them of their reſolution in calling a convention, and layeth the greater neceſſity upon the Eſtates, to meet the more willingly and frequently) <hi>A treacherous and damnable Plot of</hi> the Irish, English, and Scottish Papiſts, is begun to be diſcovered by the unexpected apprehending of the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi> comming from <hi>Yorke,</hi> where he had kept his meetings and correſpondence by Letters, with certaine Popish Lords his Confederates, and amongſt others, with the Earle of <hi>Nithiſdail</hi> and Viſcount of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyne,</hi> their devillish deſignes and devices are come to light, and brought to our knowledge, partly by Letters from <hi>Ireland,</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the depoſition and confeſſion of a ſervant of the Earle of <hi>Antrims,</hi> and partly by Letters which were found in the Earle his own pockets, all ſent to them from <hi>Ireland:</hi> His ſervant, who was hanged at <hi>Carrick-Fergus,</hi> the day of May, deponed (as the Letters bear) before and at the time of his death, <hi>That the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne was to reconcile the Engliſh and Iriſh in</hi> Ireland, <hi>that they by their joynt power, having expelled the Scots, the Iriſh For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces there might be ſent against the Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>to deal</hi> with ſome fit inſtrument there, by all their ſtrength to ſurprize the Iſles and the High-Lands, and to depopulate and waſte ſo much of this Kingdom as their power could extend unto, being aſſured of the like dealing in the North, by the Papiſts and their
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:132705:30"/> aſſiſtance there. And to have a Magazine at <hi>Carlile</hi> for twenty thouſand men, to fall in with an hoſtility upon the ſouth parts of this Kingdom. The Letters ſent from <hi>Nithiſdail</hi> and <hi>Aboyne,</hi> all written and ſubſcribed by their hands to the Earle of <hi>Antrim,</hi> and found with him, although in ſome things covertly written, do carry thus much expreſly, that for furtherance of the deſigne and point reſolv'd on, there was aſſiſtance aſſured from the Iſles, and from the North and South of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that Ammunition and Armes, without which they think their ſervice uſeleſſe, were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be ſent to the North, and other parts of this Kingdom, and that Popish Officers were commanded, and had undertaken to goe into <hi>Scotland;</hi> of which we are informed, ſome are already gone to the North, for ſtopping and diſappointing ſo far as may be for the preſent (till the ſame divine providence make a more full diſcovery) the attempts and devices of this unnaturall and bloody confederacy and conjuration. As the Lords of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Privy Councell have given order that <hi>Nithiſdail</hi> and <hi>Aboyne</hi> be cited, and criminally purſued of high Treaſon, and have made the ſame as a matter of publike and moſt high importance known to his Majeſtie, and to the Parliament of <hi>England:</hi> ſo they and the Commiſſioners of Peace alſo, for acquitting themſelves in their truſt, and for the ſafety of the Kingdome, doe make the ſame pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely known to all his Majeſties good Subjects, that being fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned of their danger, they may be upon their guards, and prepared againſt forraign invaſion, and inteſtine plots and inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: And eſpecially, that the Noble men, Commiſſioners of Shires, and Borroughs, perceiving greater and more apparent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the approaching convention then they could have wished or expected, may at the day formerly appointed, meet in ſuch celerity, and with ſuch publike affection and diſpoſition of heart, as the preſent condition of affairs doth require, and call for at their hands, and as beſeemeth the lovers of their Religion, King, and Countrey, which are in ſo great danger, from Papiſts, Atheiſts, and other degenerated Countrey-men, who are no leſſe inraged againſt this Kingdom, even ſince the late Reformation of this Kirk, then were their Predeceſſours at the firſt reformation of Religion, when their negotiating was ſo reſtleſſe, and their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:132705:30"/> ſo many, and malicious againſt the work of God in this Land: <hi>nor is it to be paſt without obſervation, that while His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty is making a publike Declaration of His intentions to defend and maintaine the Religion, Rights, and Liberties of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> according to the Lawes Civill and Eccleſiaſtick, <hi>the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are conſpiring, plotting, and practiſing againſt the Religion,</hi> Rights, and Liberties eſtabliſhed, and againſt the lives of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties good Subjects; whereby they doe really manifeſt to the world what the Kings Majeſtie againſt his Declarations, and his Subjects againſt their confidence grounded thereupon, may look for from their malice and power, if they shall continue in Armes, and, (which God forbid) if they shall prevaile in the end. And whereas the Lords of Councell are informed, That the late Act of Councell for publishing his Majeſties Declaration is miſtaken by ſundry, as a Declaration of their owne judgement, concerning the proceedings of another Kingdom; For preventing of this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, they think fit to remember and declare, according to the act of Councell in January laſt, ſhewing that their Lordships giving Warrant to print any Paper comming from his Majeſtie, or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England,</hi> did not import their approbation of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thereof: That they did on the firſt of June, both remember the ſamine, and expreſſe their intention in this publication to be far from taking on them to judge of the proceedings of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of another Kingdom; but onely to thank his Majeſtie for his gracious expreſſions towards the preſervation of the Rights and Liberties of this Kingdom: And ordain this to be printed and published at the Market-Croſſe of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and all other Burghs within this Kingdom, for the information of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Subjects within the ſame.</p>
            <div type="order_to_print">
               <head>At <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the ninth day of June 1643.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Lords of his Majeſties Privy-Councell and Commiſſioners for conſerving the Articles of the Treaty, ordain this following Declaration to be printed and publiſhed at the Market-Croſſe of</hi> Edinburgh, <hi>and other Burghs of this Kingdom, for the information of all his Majeſties good Subjects within the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Arch. Primroſe,</hi> Cler. <hi>S.</hi> Conſ. &amp; Commiſ.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:132705:31"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, my very Noble friends, theſe, On the Iriſh Committee of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> preſent theſe with due reſpect.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>EXpect nothing from your honours reall and faithfull ſervant in this adverſe time, but what brings comfort; In my laſt expedition againſt the Rebels, occaſioned by ſudden intelligence, I went forth with two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand foot, and three hundred horſe, being provided for ten daies, at no greater allowance then ſeven ounces of meale a day for a ſouldier, our ſcarcity being ſo great, that for want of victuals and ſhooes we were unable to doe the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice we wish, or your honours expect from us; Nevertheleſſe our fortune was ſuch that with this ſmall party, without Cannon, for want of carriage horſes, we beat <hi>Owen M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> art Oneale,</hi> Sir <hi>Philome Oneale,</hi> and <hi>Owen M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> art</hi> the Generall his ſonne, being all joyned together with their Forces, and forced them to returne upon <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemount;</hi> after quitting the Generals houſe to be ſpoyled and burus by us, with the whole houſes in <hi>Lochgall,</hi> being the beſt Plantation in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and ſtraiteſt for defence of the Rebels; At the ſame time Colonell <hi>Hoome</hi> with a party of five hundred men was buſied in beleaguering the Caſtle of <hi>Newcaſtle:</hi> the receipt of all the <hi>Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence comes from England to the Rebels in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> where it was my good fortune in time of treaty there, to triſt a Barke come from the Iſle of Man, with that treacherous Papiſt the Earle of <hi>Antrim,</hi> whoſe brother <hi>Alexander was ſent before by the Queenes Majesty from Yorke,</hi> to make way for the Earle, in negotiating betwixt her Majeſties Army in the North of <hi>England,</hi> and the Papiſts on the borders of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the Iſles of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the North parts thereof, and with the Rebels in <hi>Ireland, Their plot being ſet downe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:132705:31"/> by the Queenes Majeſties conſent, for the ruine of Religion, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw of His Majeſties loyall Subjects in all the three Dominions, as evidently doth appeare by the Letters, Characters, Paſſes, and Papers found with the Earle,</hi> directed by me to the Councell of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Generall. It becommeth me as the ſervant of the publique, intruſted with your Commiſſion under the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> to enforme truly your honours of the great prejudice the cauſe in hand ſuffers by your honours neglect of this Army, being unable to doe ſervice as might be expected from them, if they received the halfe of the allowance your Souldiers receive at <hi>Dublyn,</hi> and had allowance for ſome horſes for carriage; in my opinion, in ſix weekes time we could ſettle Garriſons in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and thereafter overſway your enemies elſewhere in any part within his Majeſties Dominions, where your enemies prevailed moſt. Therefore my weake opinion is, this Army not be neglected, wherein conſiſts ſo much of your peace and ſafety, having no friends you can repoſe into more then in us, who are deſirous to ſee Religion flouriſh, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels ſubjected to obedience, and his Majeſties Throne eſtablished in deſpight of Papiſts, and of wicked Councell, miſ-leading his Majeſty, to the ruine of his Dominions, who would be the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Prince in the World, if the Lord would moue his heart to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the Counſell of thoſe, sheds their blood for his honour. The Earle of <hi>Antrim</hi> shall God willing be kept cloſe in the Caſtle of <hi>Carrickfergus,</hi> till I be acquainted from your honours concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him, what courſe shall be taken with him: and the Traytor conveyed him laſt away, is to be executed, ſince we can extort no diſcovery from him then is contained in the Papers ſent to <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſo recommending your honours, and your weighty affaires to the direction and protection of the Almighty, deſirous to heare from you, I remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yourr moſt humble, truly affectionate, and reall ſervant, ROBERT MONRO, Generall Major.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Carrikfergus,</hi> 
                  <date>May 23, 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="affidavit">
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:132705:32"/>
            <head>The Examination of <hi>John Dod Clerke,</hi> taken by a ſelect Committee of the Houſe of Commons, July 8. 1643.</head>
            <p>SAith, that after he had ſuffered many miſeries i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> he repayred into this Kingdome, and ſome occaſions carrying him to <hi>Oxford,</hi> he ſtayed there ſeven weekes, and came out of <hi>Oxford,</hi> June 13. 1643. That du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his ſtay there, he ſaw a great number of Iriſh rebels whom he very well knew to have had an hand in the moſt barbarous actions of that rebellion, as the daſhing of ſmall infants in pieces, the ripping up of women with child, and the like: among whom was one <hi>Thomas Brady,</hi> who at <hi>Turbet</hi> in the County of <hi>Cavan</hi> in the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> within ſeven miles where this ſaid examinat lived, as 36 old men, women, and children, not able to flie, were paſſing over a bridge, cauſed them all to be thrown into the water, where they were all drowned. That this <hi>Brady</hi> is now at <hi>Oxford,</hi> in great favour, and Serjeant-major to Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Percy</hi> his Regiment: That he ſaw there three Franciſcan Fryers, namely, <hi>Bryan ô Gormuti, Anthony mac Geoghagan,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Nuegent;</hi> and three Jeſuits, namely, <hi>Laurence Sutton, Philip Roche,</hi> and <hi>Edmund ô Rely,</hi> who were all very earneſt for the cauſe and daily encouraging the ſouldiers to fight againſt the Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads; and for that purpoſe have lyſted themſelves in the Lord <hi>Dillons</hi> Troupe (as was affirmed by divers;) they goe very brave and are called Cornets. That there are daily and publique meetings at Maſſe, in almoſt every ſtreet there; and verily beleeves in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that for one Sermon preached there are foure Maſſes ſaid now at <hi>Oxford.</hi> That he ſaw Sir <hi>Iohn Dungan</hi> there (a man accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of high treaſon in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for partaking in that rebellion, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:132705:32"/> fled into <hi>England</hi>) who had a Commiſſion for a Troop of horſe. The Lord <hi>Barnewall</hi> of <hi>Trimlettſtowne,</hi> and his ſonne, who hath a Commiſſion for a Troope of horſe, and is now gone into <hi>Wales</hi> to raiſe them; a ſonne of the Lord <hi>Neutervills,</hi> who hath gotten a command likewiſe. That as neere as he can poſſibly compute, there was then at <hi>Oxford</hi> about 3000 Irish rebels; and that moſt of the Kings life-guard are Irish.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Dod.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
